Oh, actually.
Khuyen, welcome to Talk Python To Me.
Great to have you here.
I'm happy to be here.
Yes, I'm happy to have you here.
It's going to be a super fun data science topic.
You've got a really cool project over at CodeCut.ai.
And one of our listeners reached out and said, you have Khuyen on because she's doing amazing stuff over at CodeCut.ai.
And I'm really getting a lot of value out of it.
And I'd love to hear more about this project and maybe dive into some of the topics there.
So we're going to have a really great time talking about that.
But before we get to those, really quick introduction for everyone.
Who are you?
Yeah.
Hi, everybody.
I'm Quynh Truong.
I'm a developer advocate at Nixler.
I am also the founder of CodeCut, where I share daily tips on both LinkedIn and through my newsletter.
And I send out short tips, which have about data science and Python in form of code snippets.
That is very easy to digest in two minutes, three times per week.
Three times a week.
That's a lot.
Yes, it's a lot of work.
But I have been doing it for four years, I think.
So I have been writing tips, writing Python snippets for like basically every day of the week on the weekday for four years.
Yeah, very fun.
And you also have longer form articles there.
Yes, that is correct.
I also enjoy writing long form articles that dive deeper into open source.
So majority of the time, like 95% of the time, I write about open source Python data science related tools.
So very specific.
And I like to really explore how, why should data scientists use this tool and how they use it.
And my assumption for every article is data scientists are very busy.
And if they only have five minutes to read this article, they will be able to get some takeaway from this tool and be able to apply right away.
So you will see that as a common theme for snippets, micro snippets, as well as newsletter, like very short, very easy to digest, as well as article, even though it's long form, but also very, like if they want to, they can skim it, get something out of it.
Or if they really want to like die different, you can sit down and like call along.
And both will work for getting out of it.
Yeah, I agree.
I read a bunch of your articles and I think you can certainly get it a lot even if you just have only time to skim them.
I learned a couple of extra new tools.
I think that we're going to have a lot of fun to talk about as well.
So how do people get your code snippets?
Is that through your newsletter or how you do that?
Yeah, people get my code snippets through my newsletter.
And if you go to the front page, see if you find how it looks like.
Yes, that's how it looks.
So just for the audience who's listening, so the form of my newsletter is I would.
So I would extract some specific feature out of the tool, right?
Because if one tool can have many features and you don't want to talk about all the features in one code snippet, it will be really difficult to digest.
So I pick one feature. I compare it with something that people already know.
For example, in the screen, we see we are comparing between a regular expression, RedX, Library and DFLIP.
and we try we I want to so compare something people already know something that is lesser know to highlight okay we see the typical problem with the tool that people all know and here's a solution and this tool offer the solution and so that's for co-snipeat my my philosophy when it comes to teaching people is it's better to show than to tell so I put a lot of effort into making it very easy for people to when they look at the code snippet they can understand but of course there's supported text so if you scroll down a bit more so you can see the format of it yeah we is the problem solution. The problem is, I will just read it out loud here, RedX pre-processing achieves exact matching but fails completely on typos like iPhone 14 Pro with like 2 double R max.
Dolution deeply provides similarity scoring that tolerates typos and character variations, enabling approximate matching where uh red x pairs and they can do the full article fair one but it's yeah that's cool mean to be digested within the newsletter yeah i think you could you could
probably read that and get a good uh bit of information on that in like one minute that's really nice and the idea you're highlighting here is like sure you can search if you're doing data science text nlp type of stuff if you search with regular expressions you might find things But what if the spacing is different between them or somebody puts a comma or they put iPhone 14 without a space between the 14 and the iPhone, right?
Like all those things are really tricky to catch every variation.
So there's better tools like DiffLib, which we'll probably talk about again later in an article, right?
And in the article, I highlight a lot more tools.
So it's from like Red X to DiffLib.
And then if you want to like even better than fuzzy matching, right?
And then if even you want semantic capture, a capture, and that's another tool.
And then of course you can go down all the spaCy route and into LLMs and like the whole spectrum, right?
But just knowing about this, because sometimes you don't, you don't want full machine learning.
You just want kind of like regular expressions, but not so hard.
That's correct.
like something that get the job done.
To me, the idea tool is something that works right out of the box without a lot of boilerplate code and not too many dependencies.
Yeah, that's really, really important.
So let's talk about the origins of CodeCut.ai.
Why did you start it?
So I started when I was in college.
so uh a couple um for you uh so i started to i didn't start the website so i started sharing my tips first i started on linkedin right so i make a commitment to myself that i'm gonna so i i initially i write a lot of articles i i push out through two to three articles on towards data science every week and I make the commitment I want to do that every week and then I was not very active on LinkedIn and then I read a book called share your work and it said how no matter how messy your work is you should just share it and I was very into open source tools and I I often just send a message to my friends, say, "Hey, check this out, this is so cool." And I was like, "What if I could share with more people?" So I started to put out some of the things that I'm excited about on LinkedIn.
And initially I was so afraid, people were like, "What are you talking about?
You don't know what you're talking about." But people also very excited about it.
And I was like, "Oh, great." I share something I'm excited about and I help some other people and everybody excited about the tool.
I love that.
So I keep doing it.
Initially, I do it like every day.
So seven days per week, share every day.
Later, I was like, okay, I'll give myself the weekend off.
But I started to do, I think, over 500 tips.
And then people was like, where can I find the old one, right?
because if you want to play, let's say, if you are interested in machine learning tools or data processing tools, how do you find it on LinkedIn? There's no way for you to categorize.
So I started to go back to most of my, there's so many, so I try as many as I can, put it into a website.
So it was at the time, I just find like some domain, it's called Math Data Simplified.
and then i just put a bunch there and then i sent out some newsletter so very very not polish at all and but i just want to have a place to capture it and then later i figure out that people was a lot of time people do have typo when they type because it's very long um url so i try to make it something very short and actually capture what I would do in cold cut.
So it become cold cut.
Yeah.
I like the aesthetic of it.
It looks nice.
It's got these soft, warm colors.
Thank you.
Yeah, I try to keep everything kind of like a cotton candy, so like blue and pink.
Yeah, cotton candy definitely comes through.
I can see that for sure.
What platform did you use to build it?
I use WordPress.
But so for articles, I'm creating a workflow where basically I write all my articles in, you know, Quarto, like Docu.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I realized that.
So I write and also I run my code in Quarto.
And then I use a WordPress API to push it to my article in blog.
so I do a lot through it's easier I don't use a WordPress editor to create the article I use VS Code through QMD but for the aesthetic why I like WordPress because I can drag and drop I'm not a front end developer so it works for me
You know it's interesting I think a lot of people who are developers get hung up feeling like they have to create their website in the same language or technology that they're an expert in you know if like if you're a python developer you're like well how do i create a website in python for my blog or you know whatever language right but i think there's a lot of value in just saying like it's just a tool i'm just going to pick it and it's going to be great like for for example i had for a long time i had my stuff in wordpress under my own domain for my blog and other things. And I finally decided to move on to Hugo, but Hugo is also not go, it's not Python, it's go. And it's just build static sites. And I think it's really, you know, it's good if you know the technology, but it's certainly not something I think people should get overly hung up on because you can, you lose out on good tools that way, right?
Yeah, exactly. And I mean, you can learn, like you can learn any language, right? If you know language you can learn you're kind of guessing and all that it's that especially now with ai
yeah yeah that's such an interesting topic i do think that's actually really changed a lot of things it's like well i could work with this but it's i'll i know i'll get stuck on something and it'll be a pro and now you can just ask an agentic ai like i'm stuck on this okay here you go you know and even if it's not perfect it really really helps sort of handle juggle different types of technology yes exactly yeah super cool so tell me more about this quarto thing this i i didn't intend to talk about this but i find it really interesting do you write in markdown do
you write html what do you write in and then publish yeah okay so i write in quarto um it is in markdown right so somebody who knows it's in markdown but it's basically really similar to The only difference is you can execute the code.
So my really favorite stack is in VS Code.
I have Quartel on the left side and then I open a doc.qmd file.
People can just imagine it's like a doc.qmd file.
But you can click the button and you can execute.
So it's very similar to a notebook, right?
But I like it.
I really enjoy writing in Markdown.
And it's just like a very clean, right?
Compared to a notebook, it's a big QMD.
You can think of like a Markdown notebook, just Markdown and you can execute the code.
After I have the image, I have the code, everything, I create some Python functions to clean it up a bit.
For example, if there's some cell that I wrote, but I don't want to show it on WordPress, on my website, I will say echo is false, right?
It's just like a comment, Python comment, on the top of the cell, as you will not show in the website, which is great.
And then I can just run publish to WordPress, and it's publish to WordPress.
What is nice about it is, let's say later, some of the content is I want to change.
Let's say in three articles, I mentioned something, like a link to something, but now it's broken.
So what I can do is I can just like, you know, click search, buy all the instances of it, update it, and then I run the function sync to WordPress, and then it will sync, right?
And, hey, I don't need to manually go through each of it.
Yeah, that's really nice.
And it'll just fix all the articles that needed to be changed.
Yeah, okay.
That's super nice.
I do think notebooks are awesome.
And the idea of notebooks are, you know, they really changed the game, I think, a lot.
But you don't necessarily want to see all of that when your goal is mostly writing, right?
Like you don't necessarily need to see all the import statements if you're only going to focus on one cell worth of code.
And it's not about the import, right?
Right.
Especially when my goal is to make it as easy as possible for data scientist scheme.
and you know when you skip it's like a long block of code you're like okay I skip I'm done like I'll read this the next time but my goal is always very small code snippet and highlight the core features of the tool and a lot of time like you need to hide unnecessary code right you know for that to happen yeah
yeah I totally agree people can get hung up on completeness and it really takes away from the essence of just like skimming it.
And also I think that this workflow, it sounds like this is one of the things that made it possible for you to do this frequently, like three, four times a week instead of getting overwhelmed, right?
Yeah, I really need to learn so many tricks in order to, I guess it's a good thing, right?
It pushed me to be more productive.
Like I learned a bunch of shortcuts because, you know, Without shortcuts, I cannot get things done quickly.
So I know a lot of VS Code shortcuts.
And I use a text expansion tool.
It's called Expanser.
And it's game changer.
I can like, you know, like view the code.
This article, right?
If you can just column, doc, something, something, like two words, and then expand the whole text.
And then you can fill in the blank.
yeah, I need to learn multiple tricks and also just automate things is how I can get it out.
But what I still find is by doing that, I can actually focus on the essence of the blog, which is to make it as easy as possible to digest as well as researching, which is very important.
Yeah, absolutely.
I love your philosophy here.
I can see why the site is popular.
And the show your work, I think that's a great philosophy as well.
It's like get it out there even if it's messy and get it out there even if it's incomplete, right?
That's the idea?
Yes, exactly.
And I really do recommend it for especially people who try to find a job, right?
At the time, kind of like another side effect of it is if you show your work, you show people what you know.
Because so many people, they know a lot, but they don't share.
And if you expect employers to find you by guessing what you know or look at your resume, it's very hard.
Because now with AI, everybody has very polished, very nice resume.
So why should they choose you over another person?
But by showing your work, by showing like even the messy one, right?
They will be able to see, okay, this is what they're interested in.
This is what makes them excited about.
And this is what they know.
Then they will be able to imagine how they can use you in their company.
And that's how, because of me sharing my articles as well as LinkedIn posts early on And when I was in college, I was able to get multiple internships in data science.
Yeah, super neat.
And, you know, you're in developer relations.
And I think there's a strong communication aspect of that as well.
And this is just another example of like, yeah, look, you want to hire me for this thing.
I'm already doing it, right?
Like one of my first important jobs I got, I was doing a lot of speaking at user groups and meetups.
They weren't called meetups then because meetup.com didn't exist, but they were meetups.
And I got a message from a company and they said, hey, we saw you talking to this place and that place and you're doing that for free.
We'd pay you if you want to do this for a job.
And I'm like, great.
Where do I sign up?
I didn't even have to apply.
They just reached out to me.
And the timing was perfect because I had quit my longtime job a week before.
And I'm like, okay, well, I was about to start looking for a new job, but I guess.
Wow, you're so brave.
You look for a new job after you quit your job.
That's very brave.
Were you intended to take a break or something?
No, I was not as brave as it sounded.
My wife got her PhD and finished, and she was getting her first professor job on the other side of the country.
And so I was like, well, I'll wait until we get there and look for a job.
because it was, you know, San Diego to New Jersey level of travel.
It was far, right?
So I figured I'll find something there.
I see.
You got a new job.
Yeah, I think I'd quit my job, but I was still working for a month, you know, because I knew I was going to be moving in a while.
And so, like, okay, guys, I'm leaving in a month, six weeks or whatever.
And about that time, people reached out.
So it was a perfect, perfect deal.
But just like you said, it's because of the stuff I was doing out in public, right?
Right.
Yeah.
Okay, so let's dive in.
Let's dive into CodeCut here.
And the idea I thought is maybe we could just go through a handful of articles.
We picked 10.
I don't know how much time we have to go through all of them.
We probably can get through all of them.
But I think this will give people an idea of what they can get from CodeCut.
but also I just think there's a bunch of interesting data science ideas and tools,
kind of like that DiffLib that we talked about.
So I think it'll be a good blend of that type of stuff to talk about.
So let's start with an article called Goodbye pip and Poetry, Why uv Might Be All That You Need.
So tell us about this, and then we can dive in a bit.
Yeah, so I think a lot of people have heard of uv, which is dependency management tool. But let me, for people who don't know about it, just kind of give some quick reason why uv might be something that you want to look into.
So a lot of data scientists know conda and no peep, right? I think poultry is a little bit less common but for a while poultry is like a modern tool that allows you to manage so many things right like dependency management and virtual environment and you can handle anyway so there's a lot of things in poultry but something that I didn't like about poultry is it's pretty slow for dependency management but when it comes to uv is quick every like it replace many things and even if you are using pip you don't want to learn new tool basically you can just use uv pip install something something and you have a speed boost um and it's yeah so i i grow entire article about uv And I also compare it with the existing tools to give people some motivation on switching it to uv.
It's so easy to switch, so why not?
Yeah, I think I am a huge fan of uv.
I actually just interviewed Charlie Marsh for his next project, pyx,
two days ago, yeah.
So uv is going to get even better.
I just pulled up the performance story for uv.
compared to poetry and pipsync and yeah it's what is that 20 times faster than poetry and way faster
than everything else yeah it's that rust because of the rust i think rust and then also they
they just rethought the caching and other they just it's rust plus a bunch of new ideas that came together to make it work really, really well. And honestly, I feel a little bit, I feel a little bit bad for the other tools. Like I'm a big fan of pip-tools and pip X and you know, those things are really great. And we'll, we'll come back and talk about them a bit, I think as well. But I think those tools laid the foundation for what uv is doing and uv, you know, sort of naturally brought these together but I whenever I think of the contributors and maintainers of those projects I feel a little bit bad because they're not getting as much love as they used to but
they're still great but uv is definitely making a splash yeah that's a good way to think about I I get excited about new tools very quickly and I don't often think about how the maintainers that the old the tools are less popular think yeah
it's the natural way of things I think but it's also tough so the speed is important, you know one thing I think is interesting, while I think this is especially interesting for data science and you touched on this already is in the I come more from like the web API side of Python I would say and over there it's been pip all day long, right? It's been pip the whole time. But in the data science side, it's really largely been Conda, Anaconda distributions, that kind of thing, Conda environments.
There's been kind of this separation. And obviously those are all pulling from the same projects that are all on GitHub and so on. But there has been a little bit of a difference. And and kind of bringing those two worlds back together what do you think yeah i agree i i
actually have an article a long time ago i think it's probably in cold cut still uh it's called people's conduct was poetry so basically i i was trying to give a very fair comparison i was in favor of poetry but you know i i compared everything and something that i've i to be honest i'm i was not a fan of Conduct and after the comparison I was not even more of a fan of Conduct because I felt like it's very heavy like you can use I think Mini Conduct so it's quicker but at the same time it installed many dependencies that you didn't ask for so it's kind of like a solution where you have a lot of dependencies out the box right but I find that a lot of you didn't ask for some dependencies and install it so you don't really have control over what being installed as well as the way that it solves dependencies or not. I find it is very slow but with so so poetry is worse better because you know it's cleaner you can see like what you put in you can see like all everything in a file like there's a separate file right one for one is PyProject.com and one is a lot, one is the other sub-dependencies.
And now uv is to me is like that, but to like poetry but better.
The fact that it can run very fast.
So one drawback of poetry was sometimes it's think very hard about and take a long time to solve, install new dependencies.
And also uv replaced with X. It's kind of like an all-in-one-place tool, which is, I think, very necessary, especially for everybody who uses Python.
but for data scientists, they already have so many things going on and tell them to learn good practices. Let's say they want to upgrade from Python 3.5 to 3.6 to 3.7.
To use other tools to do it, it seems like a lot of work. But if you can just use one tool and then and you can run it, like upgrading in one command line, then why not?
Yeah, 100%.
I think it's great.
And it has a lot of compatibility with previous workflows.
For example, you can use UVPIP install instead of using its project management thing, like with add and sync, right?
so you don't necessarily have to adopt its style.
You can just say instead of pip install, you can say uv pip install.
One of the things that used to bother me, and I honestly just haven't looked for a while, about Kondo was coming from a non-data science side.
Some of the libraries, say, like requests or flask or something like that, pyramid, those were held back quite a bit because they try to make sure there's a compatibility
between the versions that they ship through Condit,
which I think that's good for data science or reproducibility, but when it comes to web frameworks, you've got to be super on top of updates in case there's a security vulnerability.
You want to release that thing the day the vulnerability is announced.
You want to upgrade your website because as soon as it's announced, people start scanning the internet for any website that could possibly be susceptible to that problem right yeah and so like the web tools were held back a lot so that's it's one of the reasons i never really embraced conda yeah another now that
you mentioned it another i i also found it is uh one thing i didn't like about conda is you know like there's less data scientists like pandas right if this pandas version is available then a lot of time like sometimes it's not not available on conda that's one thing but another thing is data scientists they collaborate with other engineers right so at some point they need to hand over to the engineers like machine learning engineers data engineers right right use their code and i i think in my previous company like they were like they didn't use conda so for them to like need to install conda or there's a way for you to from conda to peep but then like the dependencies look very messy and it's not like a one-to-one translation sometimes it's it's not you don't get the same environment. Sure interesting yeah.
Not the trouble for handing over right and that's a reproducible is a big thing when it comes to data science so and dependencies play a big part of it so if you make it hard to reproduce the dependencies then there will be some bugs.
There will be some errors and even silent errors.
Very interesting.
Okay, next article.
Let's talk about, I think this is a big one.
Reproducibility, maintainability, that kind of thing.
What you talked about there was kind of a good lead into it, right?
It's like the production engineers need to make sure that what they're running runs the same as what the data scientists have tested and come up with.
And if the situation is different, right, the runtime environment is different, well, maybe it's going to give different answers because of different versions or something.
Yeah, exactly.
And dependency is a big thing, but there's also other things that come into it, right?
And we can talk about it, too.
Yeah, so what are some of the core ideas of reproducibility?
Yeah, so reproducibility, I think is, and at the heart of reproducibility is you want to, let's say, especially for data scientists, when they create code, right?
to create machine learning models.
They, it depends on some, there's a lot when it packages, dependencies, but also like depends on the parameters that you use.
And like, you know, even you use everything the same from experiment to experiment, it can produce slightly different accuracy.
So you want to be able to, let's say one data scientist say, I got a 0.9 accuracy.
Then they give it, head it over to their teammate to deploy it.
And then it's degrading the performance.
It's no longer have a zero accuracy.
It's probably can be, you know, go down 0.8.
And so reproducibility is very important in terms of, you know, you want people, if you produce some result, you want other people to be able to reproduce the same results so that your company can profit out of it.
But another thing is choice, right?
Let's say if you're a data scientist, you create something that is good, but then you hand it over and it's bad, then it reduces the choice from your coworkers.
The third thing about it is, let's say, if data scientists, they create some project and then later they want to reuse it, right?
like for another project, they cannot reproduce the same results.
They then it's and they need to then then it's kind of like throw it away, creating everything from scratch.
So it also time consuming.
And another big thing after publicity, I think go hand in hand is maintainability.
But yeah, you can go ahead.
Yeah, no, I totally agree.
the maintainability part is super important as well.
So what are some of the pieces that go into that?
I mean, the first thing that comes to mind for me is pinning your dependencies, either through using something like uv init, uv add, uv sync, or just a requirements.txt file, or pinning your requirements through some other means, like with poetry, but somehow clearly documenting what's used.
I think it can be easy for data scientists to just import some things in a notebook and then do a magic, well, UVPIP install that right here and let's just keep going.
But then, like, why won't it run later, you know?
Yeah.
Are you talking about maintainability or reproducibility?
Well, I was thinking maintainability.
I love it.
But both, yeah.
Yeah.
So maintainability, another thing is, another aspect that comes into maintainability is readability, right?
And I think this is a big thing for data scientists.
A lot of data scientists don't write readable code and modular code.
What you will see is like a big chunk of code with like nested if else or using global variables inside a function or not using function at all.
And there's a lot of duplicate in the code.
and I mean that is great for quick experimentation like you want to get something out of it but at the same time it's create a lot of technical debt in terms of uh that's musical thing that really reach you not readable right so read it and I can go deeper I just want to list it out, readability and then reproducibility. Readability, you want your code to be readable because data scientists collaborate with other engineers. And also another problem I saw is data scientists cannot read their old code in a couple months. They forgot. They're really like, what did I write? And they spend quite a bit of time to understand what they write. And if they cannot understand or they don't trust it, right? If you don't understand in a full level, you cannot trust it and you cannot use it for the next project. A lot of times they write things from scratch again. So readability also, if your code is not written well, readability and reproducibility. It's harder to reproduce the same results because, let's say global variables, you use global variables and it affects your code, then it's hard. You might introduce some external factors that make the code different the next time you run. So maintainability is very important and And that comes with, sorry, readable code, version control, dependencies management, configuration management.
Meaning you don't want to hot code the values into your code.
Yeah, this is a really great article here because it shows you so many tools and techniques, I think.
Yeah, thank you.
And I also, so writing a maintainable data science project has been my passion for a long period of time.
And it actually has become a book like this, this is the article form.
But I also recently wrote a book about this, finished a book about this.
It's called Production Ready Data Science.
Yeah, congratulations.
That's amazing.
When did you finish it?
When did you publish it?
two months ago, I think.
Okay, so really recently, yeah.
Very recently, yeah.
It took me quite a while.
I have all the materials because I've been writing about this.
So I have so many materials who put it together and also make it less in like the article style, explaining more of the why before the how is also what I focus a lot on this book.
Yeah, that's a super important part.
now I you know I am a huge fan of thinking a lot about readability and spending a lot of time on readability and I agree with you I think we're on the same page for sure on that one because if your code is not readable that doesn't mean it can't be read it just means it's harder to read right if your code is not readable it's harder to maintain it, it's harder to see the bug It's harder to read.
All the things that you've pointed out.
And I think it's a little bit ironic that the notebook style of development that is meant to communicate, like it's supposed to be more communication compared to regular programming, right?
It's got the markdown cells.
It's got the pictures.
It's got little tables for like df.head, that kind of stuff, right?
Its natural way of programming it leads to less maintainable reusable code, right?
Because it does not encourage functions.
So it's really hard to do reuse if you don't think, oh, maybe I need to write a function in this cell, collapse the cell, and then use the function later, right?
That happens, but not very much.
I was doing some research for, or just looking around really, research is a little bit high, Putting it in a high position compared to what it was.
I was looking around for some examples, and I found this really cool JPL collection of notebooks for studying, I think galaxies, like studying the brightness of galaxies and trying to understand things about them.
And they had a bunch of cool notebooks in there, and they were like 1,500 lines of code and stuff in there.
One function.
One.
Wow.
like oh that is probably i mean maybe this is necessary but it's probably not necessary and this is jpl right this is like a polished published thing not just a random notebook i ran across right uh the jet propulsion laboratory in pasadena which is i consider them to be pretty amazing so yeah maybe speak through a little bit about that like this maintainability thing in juxtaposition
with like notebook style yeah definitely i that's the thing i before i i think five years ago i wrote an article that got very popular but also a lot of controversy is called i think something about like seven reasons why i switched from notebook to python script something but so anyway so the thing about notebook is A lot of people argue, yeah, you can write functions.
It's just Python, right?
You can write functions.
You can write whatever you want, just like a Python script.
But the interactive style of it discourages you from doing it.
Like, why should I write a function when I can just see the result and then I build upon it?
Because what is so great about it is you can see the result and then you can build up upon it in the next cell, next cell, next cell. So people are less likely to build a function which like if you create a function then like it's hidden inside a function, it's not execute the code. So that's one thing. Another thing problematic about notebook is it's encouraged hard coding. You know like a lot of time because if you want to see the Another thing is a very big problem is self execution.
If you execute self, the fact that it gives you the ability to execute in different orders is nice, but also a disadvantage in a way that if you run it in the wrong order, then And it will, like, you can get some results right now that is different from results that you want to run.
Right.
If you forget to run a particular cell, you go back up, run that to refresh it, and then you skip back down.
Something in the middle was important, and you don't rerun it.
That's probably not good.
Yeah, exactly.
And I remember when I worked in Notebook before, it just gave me a headache because I would run something.
I said, oh, did I rerun this?
did i run that store did i not just to make sure i will run it so it's something and and then later when i come back to notebook i was like i'm not gonna reuse this notebook again because i don't
know what's going on here yeah i don't want to people to think that i'm completely anti notebook i'm not but i do think that there are some techniques and some tips that you can use so when i was riffing on functions one thing i think you could do and you touched on it as well is you could take the parts of your code that you want to reuse and put that in a python script next to your notebook and import it right and then you can use it a lot of times i think there's a bunch of cells in notebooks that don't really have to do with the presentation or the important part they're just there like well i need to load this thing or i need to like clean up that or or something and it has to go before what you actually want to show people if you could put that in a script then you could just import it and then show the important part.
It's more readable, more reusable.
It's more modular.
In all ways, almost, it's better.
Yes, I agree.
The thing about, yeah, Sam, like notebook is great.
It's very good for presentation.
But I think the problem is a lot of time people use it more than what it's supposed to desire for, which is, to me, it's prototype, right?
It's to showcase something.
to showcase it with either non-technical or technical people.
It's not used for like everything.
And I think that's a problem.
Like a lot of data scientists use it for everything, including writing production, writing code.
And again, that's another argument, right?
Like can you, should you write production, writing code in notebook?
And Netflix did that.
Netflix create production, writing code in notebooks.
And that's great.
Paper mill and all that stuff.
Yeah.
Yeah, that technology allows you to do it.
I feel like it's still...
At the same time, it's a tool that if you use it right, then it will serve you.
Yeah, it's interesting.
Speaking of tools, I know you've written about, talked a little bit about Marimo.
What do you think about that?
I think this is a really interesting one.
I just did a course called Just Enough Python and it's software engineering for data scientists.
Nice.
And I was trying, thanks, yeah.
And it's like, okay, a lot of themes that you talk about as well, like you should probably learn Git, you know, and so on.
But one of the things I really struggled with was I really wanted to use Marimo as the foundation, but, you know, 90% or more data scientists use Jupyter.
So I ended up using Jupyter, but I think Marimo actually might be a little bit better in terms of software engineering and a little bit better in terms of this order of operations you talked about, like, because Marimo tracks like, hey, this cell depends upon that cell.
So if you rerun this one, we got to rerun that one first.
It'll catch those kind of things.
But you want to maybe talk about this real quick?
Because I know you wrote about it a little bit.
Yeah, I really like Marimo.
I think it's great.
It has been, so I was actually in the middle of writing the book, right?
And I know that data scientists love Notebook and I don't want to be like, hey, let's just write Python script.
But at the same time, I really think that Notebook is really hard to write production radicals.
And that's, you know, my book is about production radicals.
So how do you find the middle ground
between, you know, an interactive version of Notebook and production radicals.
So Marimo came out and I dig deep into it.
solve a lot of problems and first is a self-execution order right so the problem in notebook is let's say you sell one, sell two, sell three you change something in cell one for example you all run it but then you change something in cell one if you forgot to rerun cell three then you know the result is not going to reflect what you have changed in cell one but with Marimold it can detect the dependencies and if you change cell 1 and cell 3 depend on cell 1, depend on the variable in cell 1, then it will execute it automatically which is great.
Another big thing is notebook, not this advantage, notebook is it is javascript right so it's very uh big uh unreadable um hard to if you want to use it for
hand it over reuse it it's really right it's so common to get a git conflict when you try to pull a new version just because the output has changed and that shouldn't even be taken into account
and yeah that shouldn't be taken into account and also the output can be big but with Marimo Notebook is just a Python script under the hood.
So you have a, you have, and what great thing about Python script is that you can reuse it.
You can like import it in another Python script, but also for CI/CD, right?
And you can write unit tests, you know, like with unit tests is important, but with in Notebook, you can write unit tests.
There's a hack around, but it's a hack.
And a lot of times people need to put their test inside notebook, which is not modular, right?
It's not.
It makes it very messy with code and then test inside the same place.
But if you write notebook that is Python script under the hood, then you can write unit tests and you can run it with pytest.
Yeah, very cool.
I think this is a neat one.
I generally wanted to use it, but I'm like, but at the same time, I probably got to speak the same language of the people doing that.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, yeah.
So another thing I want to talk about here, actually this maintainability article, it's just got so much good stuff in it.
Something I think that might be new to folks is Hydra, right?
Let's talk about this idea of managing configuration files with Hydra.
Yeah, I love Hydra. Hydra is developed by Facebook research and I think I use it.
It has been my two goals. I have some core tools. I go back for every data science project and Hydra is one of them.
something that so for i guess so if you think about hydra is a configuration management tool you can write your configuration inside a yaml file and then you can you know like call things you can access the variables inside the yaml file inside a python script that is nothing new right people know about Like there's a YAML muting library in Python that allows you to work with YAML.
But something I like about Hyder a lot is reduce the boilerplate code.
So you can just add like a decorator to your Python function, and then it will be able to access everything underneath inside the Python function.
And instead of using a brackets notation, for example, if to access a nested value, you might need to use mutual nested function.
But instead, you can use dot notation, which is very clean.
Other things are-- oh, you can-- as your project getting bigger, right?
mean for a small project maybe a YAML is enough but as your project getting bigger let's say you have you want to be able to use especially in like data science experimentation you want to use different values you want to experiment with different way of processing you want to experiment with different parameters for your models and that can get messy your YAML file become very big So a good way to handle this is you want to break it into smaller configuration.
But if you want to do that without Hydra, then you need to write Python functions to access it, to composite it, to put the pieces of puzzle together. With Hydra, basically everything is handled for you.
So you can break it apart and then you can refer to different part of the pieces.
You can like in one YAML file, you can refer to the other part of the YAML file.
It's kind of like the import, right?
Import in Python.
And you can override it.
Another thing I realized, you can override the parameter from the command line.
Yeah, that's a cool feature.
Yeah.
So you don't need to go back into the, because a lot of time you want to experiment different parameters or inside the production environment and the development environment you might use different parameters and if you can override from the command line which is used a lot in you know different platforms then that that will be amazing yeah it's super neat basically
provide a bunch of default values instead of hard coding them and then if you need to override them you could do that through the command line or you could just do it in code or whatever right yeah exactly yeah excellent and you're bringing it all together here in your article uv run process py and then over so you got your hydra you got your uv run coming together all that stuff so you actually have a whole article i originally started talking about it because it was in the maintainability section but you have a whole article called hydra for python configuration
right? Well, the other article is more like a high level, but then I have smaller articles that talk about each tool. Super. Okay. Well, we're not making very good progress through this,
but that's okay. Because these are really interesting topics. Another one that you talk a lot about is doing proper logging. And you recommend Log Guru, which I love Log Guru. I
but then I've been slowly moving towards log guru nice yeah I really like so another thing about you know like a lot of data scientists they use print which nothing wrong with print like in fact you you you shouldn't use I think it's overkill you use print in a notebook right but when it comes to like if you want to write production radical if you have a bunch of print because a lot of time you had debugging prints right and if yeah you can go back and delete them and everything but wouldn't it be great but then like if you go back to development environment then you need to like put it back or if you don't do it at all if you keep all the print inside your code you go into development now you have a bunch of noise when you see the output so With logging, just a simple way of thinking about, I think a big advantage of logging is you can do logging and you can use different modes like debug, info, warning, error.
So you can set the level based on, you can show, let's say if you're going to your in development environment, you want to show the debug level. If you're going to the production environment, then you might want to do like the info level only.
But one drawback of logging is I think it's tech a lot, quite a bit of boilerplate code.
That's the first thing. So it really, even if you can copy and paste, even it's like one barrier, you know like one barrier to use logging why should i do all these code when i can just use print
right it's got like you got to register handlers and all sorts of funky stuff yeah
and but what what if you can have the advantage of print like so easy to use and the benefit of logging then that's why i'm such a big fan of blocker rule which have the best of both world and other things that it allows is beautiful out of the box.
So the login output, it looks colorful.
It's very easy to see.
With a standard login, you need to do a lot of, you know, what do you want to show?
You want to show this, you want to show the lines of code, you want to show the function, whereas the output is coming from all those configurations.
with Logger. You can just say from Logger.import logger and then logger.info something something and the output is very beautiful.
Yeah, I really like it.
You can basically just if you wanted to kind of keep your print style you don't have to you can just import it and use it and it just prints, right?
Yeah.
The other thing, like you pointed out this is a super big for people who are primarily data scientists who haven't worked with logging a lot or new programming, instead of just saying logger print, you say logger debug or logger info or logger error.
And then you can say, production, just show me the errors.
Or, hey, something's going wrong.
Actually, show me all the warnings and the info.
And you can dial it up and down without changing the code.
So you can leave your effective print statements there and just turn them off with a configuration, maybe with Hydra, who knows?
Yeah.
Yeah, really nice.
And the color.
the color is very nice as well it's very colorful yeah it's and the color persists through files
by the way right so if you have log guru log into a file and then you tail the file in your terminal
you see the color still which is awesome oh wow i didn't know that that's a new thing for me
yeah yeah because some of my stuff is all logging um with log guru and i tell and the color comes through. And it's so much easier. Like, for example, on the website, one of the things that I'm logging to a separate file is, what are the requests? What is the response time? What is the status code? Is it a 500? Is it 200? Is it a 300? You know, whatever, right? All that.
And so I'll actually have it change the color based on what happens. So if the message is a 500, it's a different color than if it's a 200. Or if the response time is over 500 milliseconds,
it changes color to like a warning sign versus if it's under.
And all that stuff comes through, and it's so nice with Log Guru.
So nice, yeah, especially when you have a lot of logs, and that is very useful.
Yeah, absolutely.
Okay.
Git, let's talk about source control.
Yeah, version control, I think, is huge.
is very useful and it's very important for data scientists but I don't see it's being used enough.
I was a machine learning engineer in Accenture and working with clients so I was building kind of like a data science environment, data science tool that integrated with say AWS SageMaker and it's funny how many data scientists are not using Git and like their multiple data science team and they want to communicate with each other, you know they want to share their work but then every time they want to share their work it's so hard for them because they don't have a source version control which surprised me you know it's a big client I mean it's a big point why don't they use good and if they do it's not very good practices so That's why I want to educate data scientists more about Git.
And to me, Git is so important for several reasons.
First, let's say if you do something, you mess up some code.
Let me give an example of data scientists. They write a model, There are code that produces a model that works great.
Then later they want to test the parameters, maybe experiment with different types of processing, see if the model performance can increase.
And they mess it up as the model decreases in performance.
And they have added two or three files.
Now they need to revert it.
And if you don't already save the last version that was working, you cannot just revert to it.
But with Git, you can do multiple things.
If you're just a solo data scientist, then you can revert it to the last working version.
But if you work with all the data scientists, then you can share, you can also collaborate with them.
Different data scientists can work on different versions and then all different features.
And when they're ready for it to be published, then they can merge it together, which is so much better when you do it with Git than manually going life to life.
I think I agree with you that I think data scientists don't use source control or version control enough.
And I think that even when people work alone on their own project, they should use Git or something else.
And honestly, they should just use Git these days because it's the lingua franca of everything that people are doing.
you know what but it lets you it lets you do exactly what you're talking about and it's not just oh no i have to go back but i think a really important part of people you know speaking to the people who don't really use it that much or they only use it in their professional settings in the team maybe i think it lets you be fearless in exploring new ideas right like all right i'm commit this version and then let me just terrorize my code and like try something crazy and oh my gosh it worked great we'll keep it if it doesn't work nothing lost you can 100 go back and if people don't if they're not i mean that's a good reason even by yourself right yeah yeah exactly and it's
i feel like it's so easy uh you can do git add commit that i mean um there's a lot of thing you you can do with Git, but I think to just learn some basic, Git, Git, Git, Git, Git, Git, push.
That's it.
Yeah.
You don't have to learn.
There's maybe five or six commands you've got to learn.
Mostly your tools that you're working with.
You mentioned VS Code.
It's got awesome.
Git, Control Iteration, and PyCharm, and others.
Yeah, absolutely.
I think that's really, really nice.
Let me give you two more ideas and see how these land with you, okay?
For why I think Git is now more important than ever.
Yeah.
Number one, if you're doing any agentic coding, here's another reason to use a proper editor instead of a notebook as well, potentially.
But you can go and say, hey, AI agent, I would like you to change this and add this feature and do this thing, and it'll just go and go for 10, 15 minutes.
if what i find a lot of times with these agentic coding things is they make great progress you're like wow this is amazing it makes more great project like how is this even possible i live in the future and then the next step is oh no it broke it all you know what i mean you're like
yeah yeah you have the same experience yes and i love that you go into this topic because that's kind of i think of the mathematics i have been mentioned it's more important than ever now that you have AI, you're working with AI.
Because two different things, right?
A lot of time, you wanted to do something, and then it broke.
So you want to go back to the previous version.
That's one thing.
Another thing is if you commit very frequently, then you can see what it changed.
And you can catch it before you commit it or you push.
Because so many, I think it's so frequently that I saw it do something that is not optimal.
For example, multiple nested, like with AI, a lot of time it over complicated solution.
It make it so many try, exact, accept, and if else, and all that it use is hot code.
It just bad practices.
But if you control, you use version control, you can see like the difference, like the last code and the new code, and you can catch it before you commit.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's more important than ever.
Yeah, you're 100% right.
You're right on it.
I find that when I'm doing the agentic coding side of things, I actually have the source control tab open in my editor.
Not the files tab, but the source control.
And as it's going, I'll see what files are changed, and I'll start looking at the diffs.
Even while it's still working, I'm like, oh, it's on a good path.
Oh, no, it shouldn't be doing this.
And either you ask it to fix it, or you just go, no, I'm reverting it.
Yeah, I added a feature to the website.
Not a super big one, but kind of touched a lot of files.
I think there was 15 commits to achieve that change because every time a major, I'm like, okay, the AI has gotten something right.
I'm like, save that to get, because it's exactly like you described.
It's awesome.
Yeah, I experienced the same.
I would have so many commits for one feature change because also something that i tell to do is uh you know just let's say if i want to implement like a something i really like to do is go very thoroughly with like planning very very thoroughly in advance before even code to ensure like everything is uh what i expected and then i let it run right um and what i did it depends on what i run i do but recently i try to develop like a workflow to go from you know my code into newsletter so i i want to implement something uh and i want to be i want to be able to walk away and go back and and be able to go back to So I break into phases. Let's say I break into five phases, the easiest phase and the more complicated phase, like the nicer hair feature. Now I want to go back into each phase and see if it breaks. I want to know when it breaks. So I put every phase as it to commit.
So that if it breaks somewhere, I can go back to the previous version, which is also another thing that you can ask it to commit uh while yeah yeah that's interesting i haven't thought about
asking it to commit that's cool i'll give you one final reason to use get in the agentic world and then i think we're out of time i'm gonna have to call it but this has been a great conversation i one other thing you talked about like oh it's made good progress and then something didn't work and you can actually tell it you gave your example let me make this more concrete you gave your example of oh I made some changes as forget the AI right I made some changes it turns out that the performance fell apart I edited three files I couldn't quite remember what was wrong you could go to an agentic AI and say please look at my get local get history from this commit forward and try to understand why the performance fell apart and I bet you it will have some really good ideas if not know exactly why. And it can just, it will do what we described for us in reverse. Like it'll just look at the Git history and go, this changed, this changed. Oh, if this changed, I bet it had this effect. And then, right. So you can leverage it in reverse and feed it to the AI to get understanding
too. Yeah. Yeah. That's such a great use case that you just talk about a lot of time. You're like, okay, use GitDiv, look at the difference and tell me what's wrong. That's another thing that I use very often um also another thing on top of it is let's say it doesn't code the way you like everybody have the old preferred style to do things right so sometimes you can you can edit it and you tell it okay look at the your implementation and my implementation and like just kind of taking note of the difference um so that like the next time it will be able to create similar more similar to the style you're looking for.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a great idea.
I feel like we honestly could talk about this for hours, but we're out of time.
We're out of time, Khuyen.
So thank you for being here.
I think let's leave it with this.
Let's leave it with two things.
First of all, maybe final call to action.
People are interested in CodeCut AI, all of the stuff you've created.
How do they get started with all of your resources?
Yes.
So just go to my website.
codecut.ai and then you will see how to sign up for newsletter. There's also a book tab that if you're interested in production, read in data science, you can buy it there. It's currently on sales. It's Labor Day week so 20% off and yeah that's it. If you want to read my blog go to blog.
If you want to see a sample of my code snippet, go to short post.
Everything is very easy to navigate. Just go to post.ai.
Fantastic. All right. Well, thank you so much for being here and sharing all your experience and your work.
Really, congratulations on CodeCut. It's a cool project.
Thank you so much.
You bet. See you later.
We'll see you. Bye.