Michael Kennedy: So, hey Hugo, welcome to Talk Python.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Michael, it's such a pleasure to be here and to be back.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I think this is my third time over the years on Talk Python.
Michael Kennedy: I do think it is your third time.
Michael Kennedy: It's been a lot of fun data science things
Michael Kennedy: and I think people will see that our conversation,
Michael Kennedy: the thing that we're going to really focus on this time,
Michael Kennedy: will have evolved a little bit as the times have changed.
Michael Kennedy: I'd say since the last couple of years, the data science and the entirety of programming has gotten a little different.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Well, yeah, actually, just our conversations over the years, like, kind of are, can be a symbol of the trajectory from, like, early days of data science, PyDataStack, all of these amazing things as it went from academia to industry, then to, you know, large-scale distributed compute when I came and talked about Dask and Coiled.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And now, a couple of years after our quote-unquote GPT moment and our ChatGPT moment and our stable diffusion moment here to talk about LLM's foundation models meet data science.
Michael Kennedy: That's right.
Michael Kennedy: We've gone from local machine to cloud to AI.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Wow.
Michael Kennedy: I do see that we'll actually maybe be back.
Michael Kennedy: I see a world where we build together smaller models that maybe run locally, doing other things, maybe some servers, connecting MCP servers, connecting all these things, like little special agents.
Michael Kennedy: That's going to be something we can potentially dive into.
Michael Kennedy: We'll see.
Michael Kennedy: But I think the arc is not done.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The other thing that comes to mind is I do, and we'll get into this with AI-assisted programming, which I think superpowers people who know what they're doing, but may not be great for beginners.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I do imagine we might have boot camps or classes where you're in a cave and no access to AI or the internet and you actually learn to code on a laptop without any of this stuff.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, there's going to be a local PyPI.
Michael Kennedy: It's going to be a local set of docs.
Michael Kennedy: You know, there was this really cool app.
Michael Kennedy: Gosh, I've covered it on Python Bytes, the news podcast I do.
Michael Kennedy: And I wish I could remember, but what it would do is it had like hundreds, maybe thousands of different projects like Flask or Tailwind or whatever, span technologies.
Michael Kennedy: And you could click it and say, I want to have Flask 3.1 offline.
Michael Kennedy: Get me the docs.
Michael Kennedy: And you could create like a catalog of all these different projects you're using all offline searchable docs across.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Amazing.
Michael Kennedy: I feel like something like that might come back.
Michael Kennedy: You know what I mean?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Well, it's funny you mention that because I was chatting with Innes Montani of spaCy and Prodigy fame the other night.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: She's here in Sydney.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And she reminded me that Sebastian Ramirez of FastAPI, when he was building FastAPI originally, I think what she reminded me was they didn't have great Internet access where they were.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So they did download a lot of things at very slow speeds, then build everything locally.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: I'm reliving that, by the way, in a very weird way.
Michael Kennedy: My fiber motor died.
Michael Kennedy: And if anybody watches the video,
Michael Kennedy: they'll see that I'm actually in the library here, which is great.
Michael Kennedy: I've preserved a little private room.
Michael Kennedy: I got high-speed internet here.
Michael Kennedy: But at home, I'm tethered with one bar of LTE.
Michael Kennedy: So anything I do, it's at like 30 kilobits.
Michael Kennedy: And it brings me back to my youth.
Michael Kennedy: But boy, you got to decide what you want to do next.
Michael Kennedy: No rush.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: So I do, circling back and closing this up,
Michael Kennedy: I do think this...
Michael Kennedy: true learning the code thing is both,
Michael Kennedy: it's going to be something that comes back around.
Michael Kennedy: I think it's actually a challenge
Michael Kennedy: with all the tools and the cheats.
Michael Kennedy: I don't consider them bad cheats,
Michael Kennedy: but the things that can do the work for you,
Michael Kennedy: it requires a lot of willpower to stay focused.
Michael Kennedy: And I do think it's going to be kind of a kobold moment as well,
Michael Kennedy: where somewhere down the line,
Michael Kennedy: people are going to be like,
Michael Kennedy: we need to just get some people
Michael Kennedy: that used to type this stuff in by hand.
Michael Kennedy: And we need them to look at it
Michael Kennedy: and figure out why this doesn't work.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Without a doubt.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Learn Python the hard way.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Learn X the hard way.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Like sometimes, most things, you got to do the work, right?
Michael Kennedy: You definitely do.
Michael Kennedy: Well, Hugo, before we get into the topic too much,
Michael Kennedy: quick introduction on yourself.
Michael Kennedy: Who are you?
Michael Kennedy: I know you've been on the show a few times,
Michael Kennedy: but it's spanned many years.
Michael Kennedy: And I say it often, but it's always worth repeating.
Michael Kennedy: Like 50% of the people in the Python community
Michael Kennedy: are new over the last two years.
Michael Kennedy: Like they've only been here two years or less,
Michael Kennedy: which blows my mind.
Michael Kennedy: So those people probably want to listen to the podcast before they got into Python.
Michael Kennedy: Who are you?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So firstly, what is up, Python community?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Clearly, I'm a huge fan of Python.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Used it for many years.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Love it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Background many moons ago in scientific research, biology, math, physics.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Was working in academic research at Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Living in New York City just over a decade ago.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The data science, ML meetups, hackathons there blew my mind so much.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: moved to industry, small startup at the time,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: DataCamp, worked on curriculum, education,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: internal data science, product, wore many hats, as you do,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and worked a lot on Pythonic education there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Since then, I've been working a mixture of DevRel,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: marketing, product, a year and a half ago,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and on wonderful projects, such as Dask at Coiled with Matt Rocklin,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: then Metaflow out of Netflix with the wonderful team at Out of Bounds.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: A year and a half ago or so, space was so exciting, man.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I decided to go freelance.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And so I mixed my time, essentially helping people build, ship, and maintain AI, LLM, ML, data-powered products more generally.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I do this through consulting.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I do it through advising.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I do it through education and developer relations.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So helping open source frameworks and products reach developers and getting material that helps them.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: My former colleague and boss at Outer Bounds, Vilay, who really gets developer relations, refers to DevRel as the wisdom layer.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And he puts it firmly beside product as a pillar.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I love that because I think a lot of the time we consider education or DevRel as a necessary thing you have to do as opposed to being at a foundational pillar.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And once again, that's why I'm in such admiration of the work you do in bringing so many resources to the community at large.
Michael Kennedy: Thank you.
Michael Kennedy: And foreshadowing a little bit, I would like to kind of reinforce that quote you just said.
Michael Kennedy: And, you know, it's the wisdom layer.
Michael Kennedy: Like, as data scientists, your job is to provide insight and knowledge and trends and forecasting.
Michael Kennedy: As developers, our job is to provide solutions and things that we can use, apps and tools and whatnot.
Michael Kennedy: And I think a lot of us, myself included, get tied down in like, oh, I'm really good at coding and I'm good at this library.
Michael Kennedy: And we can kind of forget that the real first tier job of ours
Michael Kennedy: is to provide answers and solutions and apps.
Michael Kennedy: And I think a lot of the pushback on AI is like,
Michael Kennedy: it's taken my coding somewhat.
Michael Kennedy: Absolutely.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: One way I...
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Go ahead.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I was just going to add to that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: One way I think about it is it has taken my coding in some ways,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But as we'll get to, I never particularly enjoyed writing,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: love Pandas, never particularly enjoyed writing Pandas code,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: for example, incredible tool.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But if I can help me write my Pandas code, I read it,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: make sure it's all good in the hood,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and then I get to focus on building systems,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I think that's a huge win.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, 100%.
Michael Kennedy: I would be remiss to not give a little shout out
Michael Kennedy: to a couple of things that you have done or are doing.
Michael Kennedy: Let's take it chronologically.
Michael Kennedy: A while ago, you worked on the Fundamentals of Dask,
Michael Kennedy: high-performance data science course over at Talk Python.
Michael Kennedy: This course is 100% free.
Michael Kennedy: People want to dive into it and learn from you,
Michael Kennedy: they can absolutely take it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I might even take it now.
Michael Kennedy: It's just over an hour.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, people can drop in,
Michael Kennedy: and I'll be sure to put a link in the show notes for that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: That was really fun to build with you as well, Michael.
Michael Kennedy: That was during the early days of COVID,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: we were working on that.
Michael Kennedy: so you know what else do we have to do no it was really great working on it with and working on
Michael Kennedy: with you as well i appreciate that tons and then you uh since then have started a data podcast
Michael Kennedy: called vanishing ingredients exactly about that so this is a podcast and i still call it a data
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: podcast although a lot of people like you have to call it ai hugo and i'm ai is data and a lot as
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: we'll get to a lot of the principles in in building ai powered products are the same
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: modulo implementation details of building data powered products.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But it's a podcast where I talk with industry practitioners and builders
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: about what they're doing in the space, how they're building,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and essentially trying to help propagate knowledge from the bleeding edge
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: back to builders and leaders in the space.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So recently had a conversation with Hamil Hussain there,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: who he's the evals guy among other things.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But all about the eval space and how you can use evaluation in the LLM powered software
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: development lifecycle to improve your product.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I've spoken with Shell Gentleman at NASA, conversations with Jeremy Howard.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So one of the things, as I'm sure you do, I love about podcasting is I get to invite people
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I admire and who I think are awesome to chat about stuff and then share it, share it with
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: the public.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So that's the rationale there, but it's really to help people propagate knowledge, wisdom
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and skills back, back the adoption curve along the way.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: Amazing.
Michael Kennedy: That's, that's good work.
Michael Kennedy: Who should listen to it?
Michael Kennedy: Beginners, experts, data people, programmers.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's a, it's a, it's a great question.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The way I think every, everyone should listen to it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: everyone who's interested in building and shipping data-powered stuff.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And the way I actually chat about it with guests is the first third of any conversation,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I want everyone to understand, everyone who's somewhat technical.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The middle, we can go a bit deeper.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And the third is a free-for-all.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So I definitely encourage everyone to jump in.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And we've got specific episodes on evals, of course, and that type of stuff.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But we also have industry-specific episodes,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: such as chatting about what was happening
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: in the early days of shipping LLM-powered software
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: at Honeycomb or NASA and these types of places.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, that is one of the little secrets
Michael Kennedy: of being podcast hosts,
Michael Kennedy: is you get to talk to people about amazing stuff.
Michael Kennedy: You're like, huh, it'd be really cool
Michael Kennedy: to talk to the people that made that Fusion breakthrough.
Michael Kennedy: They did Python.
Michael Kennedy: Why don't we invite them and they'll draw by?
Michael Kennedy: You know, it's amazing.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah, yeah.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I get like a lot of my friends who work in the space connect me with other people.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So I'm actually chatting with a data leader at Mozilla and then the VP of learning at Duolingo soon.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So we're going to have a lot of really fun episodes coming up.
Michael Kennedy: What's up with the name Vanishing Gradients?
Michael Kennedy: Where did I come from?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah, it's a good question.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So there's the vanishing gradient problem in deep learning.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So when you do stochastic gradient descent,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you compute gradients and climb down
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: in order to optimize your neural networks.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And there's a challenge that sometimes gradients vanish
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and you stop learning.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So the rationale was, what happens when you stop learning?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And let's bring back the idea of learning in this space.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The opposite, of course, is the exploding gradients problem,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: which I also considered calling it,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: where the gradients just explode, of course.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But we went with Vanishing for that reason.
Michael Kennedy: I like that.
Michael Kennedy: That's a very clever, very subtle name.
Michael Kennedy: Nice.
Michael Kennedy: So let's talk data science in 2025.
Michael Kennedy: And to be clear, I didn't ask,
Michael Kennedy: let's talk using AI for data science.
Michael Kennedy: Let's talk data science in 2025.
Michael Kennedy: And surely, many of, I think there's two things here.
Michael Kennedy: I think there's some really interesting,
Michael Kennedy: what I don't know how we want to think about, like pure programming libraries and tools that are super powerful.
Michael Kennedy: And we could give a quick shout out to some of them.
Michael Kennedy: But then also, anytime you're exploring data, using some of these LLMs,
Michael Kennedy: and especially the agentic tooling, it's a game changer.
Michael Kennedy: So let's start with the first one.
Michael Kennedy: What tools, you know, things like pollers maybe or whatever is like jumping out at you over the last year or so that's like, wow.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Such a wonderful question. And I'll actually, I chatted about this on Vanishing Gradients with Akshay Agrawal, who built Marimo and develops Marimo, which I encourage everyone to check out.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So let's actually rewind slightly and think about what we've been using over the past decade plus plus.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it's, you know, the PyData stack, Jupyter Notebooks, Pandas, you know, SQL, SQLite databases,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and in production, maybe Postgres and these types of things.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And how has this evolved now?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: What are like modern, really cutting edge tools that we use in similar ways?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You mentioned polars.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I totally agree that this is something we're seeing a lot of activity on and a lot of use on.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: On the database side, we've got DuckDB, right?
Michael Kennedy: DuckDB is huge.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: DuckDB is making a huge impact.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And man, seriously, it's just, you know, beautiful to use, but it's so fast as well, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I mean, and that's what you want there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And then on the literate programming side,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you've got Marimo, which I'm a huge fan of.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I still use Jupyter Notebooks a lot,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but one thing Marimo affords me,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: because it's actually a.py file as well,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you can convert them.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Well, they're essentially scripts as well.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So the notebook to production story
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: is really interesting there.
Michael Kennedy: I think Marimo is super interesting.
Michael Kennedy: I think when I look at it, when I see people working with it,
Michael Kennedy: or when I work with it, the limited extent to which I have,
Michael Kennedy: it just looks smooth and polished and modern.
Michael Kennedy: And I don't know, when I use it, I feel like it's something great.
Michael Kennedy: It also solves the problem that while Jupyter Notebooks,
Michael Kennedy: Jupyter Notebooks, JupyterLab, whatever,
Michael Kennedy: in general is an incredible tool for data exploration,
Michael Kennedy: and presenting data,
Michael Kennedy: it has this crazy implicit go-to sort of sequence, right?
Michael Kennedy: Like if you don't just go run all cells
Michael Kennedy: and you start bouncing around,
Michael Kennedy: you end up potentially running stuff out of order
Michael Kennedy: or skipping a step that would have made a different answer
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: a step below.
Michael Kennedy: And that's real dangerous.
Michael Kennedy: And so Marimo uses the abstract syntax tree
Michael Kennedy: to look at dependencies across cells
Michael Kennedy: and make sure they run in order,
Michael Kennedy: which I think is an underappreciated benefit.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's like, oh, that's kind of nice.
Michael Kennedy: No, do you want the wrong answer or the right answer?
Michael Kennedy: This is really important in data science and science in general.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah, you're right.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: My understanding is it uses the AST to build a DAG of cells and executes them.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And what that means is, yeah, and it means you can't redefine something in a cell below,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but it'll give you a scratch pad to do so if you want to.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, I just want to say that's fantastic for a lot of cases.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: There are cases when you just want to explore an experiment where Jupyter Notebooks absolutely excel.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So it's not an either or here as well.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I do want to say Jupyter Notebooks, in all honesty, get a bunch of hate for that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And neither you nor I feel that way.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But I just want to be very explicit that that's not what we're saying here at all.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, I have a lot of reverence for notebooks.
Michael Kennedy: They really, not only did they change the game for data science in general, but they changed it for Python full stop.
Michael Kennedy: Like, so if you look at the popularity and the people participating in Python, like one of its really powerful aspects is people are coming from all these different angles with different ideas and perspectives and different tools they want to build and so on.
Michael Kennedy: And that's made it so rich.
Michael Kennedy: And that started basically in 2012 with the PyData stack with notebooks and all of that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah, I remember the first notebook I opened was called an IPython notebook, not even a Jupyter notebook.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And of course, it's all based around IPython also.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So we've got to give a shout out to that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And as I said, I was actually working in biology, in research at the time.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And in biology, we have notebooks, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Like you write, you put your PCR gel, you put your figures there, you write things.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: This idea of literate programming is exactly that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And what it does is it brings experimentation.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It brings scientific rigor and scientific research into computation.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And very important for this space where we are, really what we're talking about in data science, ML, AI, is the convergence of software meeting data and experimentation.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So we need new tools for this.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And notebooks are one of the most awesome examples of that.
Michael Kennedy: okay i took us down a bit of a hole with the marimo stuff because it is cool yeah anything
Michael Kennedy: else that jumps out to you i have one at the end that i want to riff on before we get off this
Michael Kennedy: topic but what else jumps out to you tools 2024 2025 that's kind of like oh that's different
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: so to step to step back a bit i we are talking about like data science with ai and that type of
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: stuff and this works both ways right like data science plays into ai and and building with
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: foundation models but i'd have to fire myself if i didn't talk about the other way which is ai
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: helping us do data science and um the tools are ai assisted the biggest tool is ai assisted
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: programming for data science which is revolutionary i i think maybe isn't even
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: as big a term as we need for this.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Absolutely groundbreaking.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: It's easy to get frustrated saying it's bad for the environment.
Michael Kennedy: I'm a good data scientist, good developer.
Michael Kennedy: I don't need this stuff.
Michael Kennedy: But for the most part, I feel like the cat is out of the bag,
Michael Kennedy: the Pandora's box is open, whatever analogy you want to use here.
Michael Kennedy: It's made such a difference.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: without a doubt and I definitely agree on climate concerns we should be having larger
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: conversations around this um you can start using smaller models and and and local models for AI
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: assisted programming they won't superpower you as as much um but there are you know I I think
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: to say all and this is to say all of AI is very bad for the climate is I suppose like saying both
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: hummers and electric cars uh in the same bucket right so but i totally agree that that's a concern
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: we need and but and the other thing though man if we're talking about like
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you know software's writing the software ai's writing the software vibe coding i don't necessarily
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: understand it guess what we were all copy and pasting from stack overflow we've been doing that
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: for a long time right um and i don't necessarily understand all that code so this is in some ways
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: scaling and superpowering that behavior.
Michael Kennedy: And it's on us.
Michael Kennedy: It's on you, it's on me, it's on everyone who uses it to either,
Michael Kennedy: and we're going to get into this more in detail later,
Michael Kennedy: use that as a learning experience or as a,
Michael Kennedy: well, I don't need to know that, whatever it says, right?
Michael Kennedy: That was true with Stack Overflow as well.
Michael Kennedy: Like you would go to Stack Overflow and you would just copy something.
Michael Kennedy: And the knock on people who would take stuff from Stack Overflow
Michael Kennedy: and paste it was they had no idea what it meant.
Michael Kennedy: They just saw that it solved the problem.
Michael Kennedy: There was even that joke keyboard that Stack Overflow created.
Michael Kennedy: All it had was like a control and a C and a V,
Michael Kennedy: and they had a Stack Overflow logo.
Michael Kennedy: It's like, this is all you need, right?
Michael Kennedy: It was hilarious, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I'd like to system prompt ChatGBT to not be so sycophantic
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and treat me like people on Stack Overflow
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: used to treat people.
Michael Kennedy: That's right.
Michael Kennedy: My ego is doing way too well today.
Michael Kennedy: I need to be beat down.
Michael Kennedy: The thing is, you could go to Stack Overflow
Michael Kennedy: wow, okay, I didn't know that.
Michael Kennedy: And then you learn it.
Michael Kennedy: And you don't need to go back to Stack Overflow
Michael Kennedy: and copy that thing
Michael Kennedy: because now you've understood something deep.
Michael Kennedy: And that's different.
Michael Kennedy: That's on you when you're copying from Stack Overflow.
Michael Kennedy: And it's on you 100 times over
Michael Kennedy: if you use these tools, right?
Michael Kennedy: Because a lot of times,
Michael Kennedy: especially the agentic stuff,
Michael Kennedy: it explains what it does.
Michael Kennedy: Like, here's what it was.
Michael Kennedy: Here's why I changed it.
Michael Kennedy: If you let that scroll by
Michael Kennedy: or you can go slow and study it
Michael Kennedy: and become smarter,
Michael Kennedy: not more brain dead.
Michael Kennedy: You know what I mean?
Michael Kennedy: Absolutely.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And for me, like, if I was getting, like,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Pandas or scikit-learn code from Stack Overflow,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I'd really, like, want to understand it
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: because that was my bread and butter.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Whereas if it was front-end stuff,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: like, I'd probably go and find the same issue,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: question time and time again.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Same with, like, environment stuff,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: like getting environments working in Jupyter Notebooks
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: or something, I just, I still can't drop that stuff.
Michael Kennedy: I know.
Michael Kennedy: I was just thinking of Bash scripts, like Shell.
Michael Kennedy: shell scripts. I'm like, you know what, this is just, I don't need to remember this. I just
Michael Kennedy: bookmark that puppy. And long as it doesn't have RMRF or something destructive in it,
Michael Kennedy: I'm just writing. Incredible. Okay. One more thing before we move on to like the AI
Michael Kennedy: depths that I think is, we got to talk about it because today is October 7th, 2025 as we record
Michael Kennedy: this, not as I release it. So, you know, I'll have to be a bit nostalgic for a few weeks.
Michael Kennedy: But today is Python Pi Day.
Michael Kennedy: Python 3.14 came out today, right?
Michael Kennedy: And one of the main features of Python 3.14
Michael Kennedy: is the free-threaded aspect being sort of officially taken in.
Michael Kennedy: And I know one of the big challenges that's been solved
Michael Kennedy: with C extensions and Rust and other stuff,
Michael Kennedy: but it's still a bit of a challenge.
Michael Kennedy: It's like, I've got a ton of data.
Michael Kennedy: I want to process it in my codes in Python.
Michael Kennedy: How do I take advantage of the 32 cores I got?
Michael Kennedy: Or do I get one 30 second of a computer?
Michael Kennedy: Right?
Michael Kennedy: And so I think starting to think about parallel programming a little bit,
Michael Kennedy: it's going to take on whatever significance it takes,
Michael Kennedy: it's going to take on more than it has traditionally.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Totally agree.
Michael Kennedy: And I think it's the data scientists who are going to need it more than anyone.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Right?
Michael Kennedy: Because our web frameworks handle that kind of stuff for us.
Michael Kennedy: They fan that out into processes and other things.
Michael Kennedy: But when you got real computational stuff, there's no IO blocking that you can work around, right?
Michael Kennedy: To leverage async, right?
Michael Kennedy: You've got to do the CPU stuff.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Exactly.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it's a really good question because I would have a trillion percent agreed with you.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I 100%, but I would have a trillion percent agreed with you pre our chat GBT moment when data scientists, ML engineers, all of these types of people.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: weren't only building products, serving models,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: that type of stuff,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but they were responsible for training as well.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And also, I think you're totally right
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: with large-scale analytics.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Think about Dask and geospatial,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: large-scale, multidimensional, geospatial,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: atmospheric data, these types of things,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and basic analytics.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I'm not even talking about machine learning there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But we have entered a regime now
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: where you can build ML and AI-powered products
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: by pinging APIs or hosting your own models
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and that type of stuff,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: whether it's from Hugging Face or wherever it may be,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: or using Olama locally.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And in that case,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I think because you're not doing the training yourself,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you're able to do a lot of things
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: without requiring massive, massive compute.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, there is a bit of a...
Michael Kennedy: It seems like a big area, but it's a bit of a thin area
Michael Kennedy: because you've got the regular programming you can do.
Michael Kennedy: Then you need that async, you need that parallelism for higher compute,
Michael Kennedy: but you don't go very far until someone says, "Fine, I'm doing it in Rust.
Michael Kennedy: I'm doing it in C++," or it's an API, and then you don't need it again.
Michael Kennedy: You know what I mean? There's like a little stratosphere sort of bit of it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Exactly.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And happy Python Pi Day.
Michael Kennedy: Yes, happy Python Pi Day.
Michael Kennedy: That's very cool.
Michael Kennedy: I have not even installed it yet today because uv has not shipped their support for it yet.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I'm so – when I mention new modern tools like Marimo and Polars and DuckDB, uv has to be in there as well.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Also very excited about other package management, but plus plus, for lack of a better term, tools like Pixie, that Wolf Volprecht.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: his his team who i know have been on the show and um you know who uh people may know from mamba
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: which helped us with conda so much um so uv is not the only only story out there solving these
Michael Kennedy: i i agree i do think i do think it's really interesting especially for the data science
Michael Kennedy: crowd because things have gotten better for those of us that use pip exclusively it's like faster
Michael Kennedy: a little bit better resolution a little bit better workflow like some of the tools are brought
Michael Kennedy: like pip-tools plus just regular pip but i think it's a bigger consideration for your side of the
Michael Kennedy: fence in that there's conda and now do you stick with conda or do you use uv like that's
Michael Kennedy: they they kind of compete more than pip did with uv i think actually i use uv i can i can i can
Michael Kennedy: say that yeah i i agree i think i think uv is pushing over the edge and then the pyx stuff
Michael Kennedy: that charlie's released if you're like an org where they help with building like the layers of
Michael Kennedy: machine models and pytorch and stuff is it's pretty interesting yeah okay i also just want to say on
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: python pi day that is so geeky and i i i would want to i do want to say show my geeky t-shirt to
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: everyone which says schrodinger's cat wanted dead and alive it's a wanted poster so speaking of
Michael Kennedy: that's perfect that's for me i i just have a sweater i'm sorry i didn't i didn't
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You're in a library, though.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: That's true.
Michael Kennedy: I'm in a library.
Michael Kennedy: It's full of books, so I'm sure something geeky is behind me.
Michael Kennedy: All right.
Michael Kennedy: So we've talked about maybe some of the other not so necessarily AI-focused tools is like what people should focus on.
Michael Kennedy: But like we both said, it's so transformative.
Michael Kennedy: And if people haven't actually tried it and seen it in action, you've got to see it to believe it.
Michael Kennedy: Because I was a skeptic until my friend's like, no, let's sit down and let me show you.
Michael Kennedy: I'm like, oh, okay, I get it.
Michael Kennedy: And so let's talk about some of the AI tools.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah, and I'd like to kind of,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I've done an initial slicing into different levels,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: which may be useful thinking through the evolution of these tools.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And so how do we use AI to help us code?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And jokingly, level zero, because we zero index here,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: is copy and pasting from Stack Overflow, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, that's not quite using AI, but it is AI is using collective wisdom as opposed to stuff in yourself, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So we've got that, okay?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But then after our ChatGPT moment, people started copy, instead of copying and pasting between Stack Overflow and their IDE, VS Code, Jupyter Notebooks, whatever it may be, people started copying and pasting between ChatGPT and the IDE.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So you would, you know, let's say you get an error message from your IDE, copy it into
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: ChatGBT, give it a bit more context, whatever it may be.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And then such as, you know, give it the code you wrote plus the error message, plus your
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: environment.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it will be pretty good at helping you depending on what packages you're using, what
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: framework.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: If you're working in PyData, absolutely fantastic, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Because, of course, it's trained on scikit-learn.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's trained on mapplotlib.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's trained on Seaborn.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's trained on spaCy, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: One of the biggest frustrations at that point was it wasn't trained on ChatGPT's current API.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So it would always give you, even if you corrected it, it would always revert to a previous OpenAI API.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Okay.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So level one, copy and pasting.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Level two, code completion in IDE.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So you can think copilot or whatever.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You're writing code and it will start suggesting things, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So that's just working your IDE.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, I think these things people probably know about.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But then level three is where things get really wild for me,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: where you actually, you have an agent in your IDE or your terminal.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So Cursor, which is a VS CodeFork, has an agent and a chat in it
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: where you can have an empty repository and say,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: hey, I want you to write a program that, you know,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: creates a rag pipeline over the documents in this subdirectory
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: or something like that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it will go and do that immediately.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It will be, when you do that, it won't be great.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It'll do all types of nonsense.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It might write lots of directories and subdirectories.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So we can talk about some of the gotchas,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but this is agentic coding where you're chatting
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and it just throws stuff in.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I will also add,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and this is something we mentioned briefly beforehand.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I don't like typing that much, to be honest.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So I use Super Whisper.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: There are other tools to do this where I dictate to it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I also have a stream deck,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: which is what we mentioned beforehand,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: which a lot of content creators use this.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's like buttons and knobs that you can assign to macros.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And so when I have a button that opens cursor,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: puts it in agent mode,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: attaches Claude, Sonnet 4.5 or Gemma 2.5,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: whatever it may be, exactly.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: that's a stream deck.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And then I have accept code buttons and reject code
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and that type of stuff.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So I can actually build a not insignificant amount of software
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: with my voice and three buttons.
Michael Kennedy: That's awesome.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Which is so powerful.
Michael Kennedy: I also, I want to just say,
Michael Kennedy: I also find that if I do dictation,
Michael Kennedy: I can be a lot more patient and thorough in a lot of ways, right?
Michael Kennedy: Like, I don't know about you,
Michael Kennedy: but I've had like RSI issues.
Michael Kennedy: So I've got to be real cognizant of like how much typing I do.
Michael Kennedy: I've got my Microsoft Sculpt ergonomic keyboard
Michael Kennedy: that I drag with me everywhere
Michael Kennedy: because square keyboards will destroy me in like a week.
Michael Kennedy: And so it lets me go on without worrying about those kinds of things.
Michael Kennedy: I use Mac Whisper, but it's super similar, I believe, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It just uses the same underlying engine.
Michael Kennedy: And that's really nice that you can...
Michael Kennedy: I do it for email. I do it for lots of things.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I love how you mentioned it does help one be more patient because yeah,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: when typing, well, when chatting with an AI,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you can get frustrated and the friction in typing and correcting yourself and
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: that type of stuff you just don't have when, when,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: when speaking natural language.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah. And I find that people, I don't, I don't, I mean,
Michael Kennedy: this is not scientific, but my experience has been that people say like,
Michael Kennedy: oh, this stuff is not good.
Michael Kennedy: It always just gives me junk results and so on is so often there's not enough
Michael Kennedy: information given. It'd be like, create me a graph, not use Plotly to create this type of graph
Michael Kennedy: with this type of focus from this data like I did before. You know what I mean? Those are really
Michael Kennedy: different things. And the more specificity you can give these tools, the better. I use a lot of AI
Michael Kennedy: stuff. And I would say I have plenty of prompts that are pages long. And I was like, here's a file.
Michael Kennedy: Here's four pages of what I want you to do with it.
Michael Kennedy: Let's go.
Michael Kennedy: And it gives not always the right answer,
Michael Kennedy: but incredible results compared to what if you just say,
Michael Kennedy: you know, analyze this or whatever.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Absolutely.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And we'll get to this when we talk about gotchas,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but having a conversation with your system
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: before getting it to write anything
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: is incredibly important and productive.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Isaac Flath, who he has a wonderful course on Maven
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: called Elite AI Assisted Coding,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: which I'm actually starting as a student this week.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and I may give a guest talk there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I don't know whether he came up with it,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but he calls it Socratic and dialogue-driven development,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: where you essentially pair program with the AI.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Don't expect it to do everything, but have conversations.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So the other thing is a lot of these agentic systems like Cursor,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: which I use daily, probably a bit too much,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you can plug into any state-of-the-art AI API.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So, you know, Sonnet 4.5 came out recently,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and the day after you could use that in cursor.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Gemini 2.5 came out a while ago.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Then you couldn't plug it in.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: GPT-5 and so on.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The other thing I just wanted to give a shout out to is Continue.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Tyler Dunn, speaking of modern tools and open source tools,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: it's like an open source cursor of sorts.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I mean, he wouldn't frame it that way,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but you can have all your own local models,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: data preserving, privacy preserving,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and use those in this way.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So just going back to this slicing though,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: level one, copy and paste code,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: level two, code completion,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: level three, agents in an IDE or terminal.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So Claude code, for example,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: can be in your terminal,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: cursor, VS Code, fork.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Level four is embedded in other tools
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: like Slack or Discord or email.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You can tag cursor in Slack to,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you know, if you notice a documentation fault,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You can tag it in Slack to fix that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Manus, you can tag in email threads now.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Level 5 is more proactive.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So all of these are reactive systems.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So you can have Cursor, for example,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and a lot of these systems,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I just use Cursor the most,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: to do code review in CI,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: in continuous integration.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So whenever I submit a PR,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Cursor can come in and do a code review there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now I'm getting a bit to future music.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Level six, we've got async or background agents that just, you know, do stuff in the background, essentially, which we're going to see a lot more of.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And then level seven, which we haven't seen so much proactive agents.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I think these are going to be huge that will just notice stuff happening in production.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Like, hey, we have this outlier here.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Oh, this didn't quite work.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: or agents that come to me on a Monday morning and be like,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: hey, check this out, check that out, check that,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: like a good colleague, right?
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, that's awesome.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But we're already at level five and kind of got background agents as well.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So we're getting, yeah, to a lot of really exciting places.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: So I'm 100% bought in up to level four, probably.
Michael Kennedy: Like certainly the agent decoding, a little bit of the code review, not so much in CI,
Michael Kennedy: but like looking at the stuff that I might ask you like, hey, what's going on here?
Michael Kennedy: Why is it like this?
Michael Kennedy: Background agents, I just haven't got there.
Michael Kennedy: They seem like they don't have enough to work with, right?
Michael Kennedy: They don't have my whole machine and all the setups and all the things they need.
Michael Kennedy: But I can see how they would be useful.
Michael Kennedy: Certainly the way you're describing like a good colleague.
Michael Kennedy: And so one example is not necessarily in software,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but background agents, and I haven't done this,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but I've got friends and colleagues
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: who've built background agents that monitor their inbox
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and will ping them, like their email, sorry,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and will cluster emails and be like,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: hey, you really should reply to this one.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: This is a prospect or a client
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: that really needs your attention right now.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, I think that kind of stuff would be really neat.
Michael Kennedy: I will throw out there now,
Michael Kennedy: this comes from Sentry, who is a sponsor of the show,
Michael Kennedy: just to be fair, but I'm not doing this
Michael Kennedy: because they sponsored it.
Michael Kennedy: they added this thing called seer that when your app collects an exception or
Michael Kennedy: something or doesn't collect and it gets dumped up there depending how you send it
Michael Kennedy: up there is it'll apply AI to whatever it receives and it'll look if you bind it
Michael Kennedy: to your github and so on it'll like try to understand the project and maybe by
Michael Kennedy: the time you get to look at the bug report it actually has a solution
Michael Kennedy: suggested as well which and it'll do a PR which that's on the verge of what you
Michael Kennedy: suggesting as this sort of like proactive buddy that's just hanging out there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Absolutely. And as I said, I do want to mention just a few gotchas. Or actually, let me just say
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: some of the really powerful use cases in data science, since we are talking about foundation
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: models for data science. Just writing code. I mean, text to SQL, all these LLMs are trained on now,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Right? So writing SQL code based on what you say or what you type in natural language.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, chat with it beforehand so that you make sure it understands your schema.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It may not be great at complex joins, this type of stuff.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Understand the system you're working with. Get a feel for how it works.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Actually think of it as, you know, like a super excited ADHD-esque, perhaps slightly autistic as well.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I mean that with all the love.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: in terms of absolute deep memory,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: be able to recall a lot of information.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And on the ADHD spectrum,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: in terms of just how it will do,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: it will spread its attention
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: over a lot of different places
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and create lots of different stuff,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: some of which may not work,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but some of which will be incredible.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So have empathy for your system in that sense.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But writing SQL code, amazing.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: PyDataStack.
Michael Kennedy: I want to run an idea by you
Michael Kennedy: and just see what you think here
Michael Kennedy: with what you just said with like,
Michael Kennedy: think of it as this super excited,
Michael Kennedy: somewhat scatterbrained junior helper,
Michael Kennedy: excited friend.
Michael Kennedy: If you had hired somebody,
Michael Kennedy: even if they went to Stanford,
Michael Kennedy: but they hadn't really done work
Michael Kennedy: on any like major data science projects
Michael Kennedy: and they came to your company
Michael Kennedy: and you gave them a job,
Michael Kennedy: would you expect 100%,
Michael Kennedy: like absolutely 100% correctness?
Michael Kennedy: And they're, no.
Michael Kennedy: So I don't know why people expect
Michael Kennedy: the AI to be literally 100%
Michael Kennedy: I think I have an idea why, but
Michael Kennedy: expecting the AI to be 100% right
Michael Kennedy: where
Michael Kennedy: it's kind of doing some of this
Michael Kennedy: human level type of reason. I mean, not thinking
Michael Kennedy: I'm not saying that, but
Michael Kennedy: this kind of problem,
Michael Kennedy: this creative problem solving,
Michael Kennedy: we should have a little bit of patience
Michael Kennedy: for if it gets it wrong, especially if we give it
Michael Kennedy: poor directions. You know what I mean?
Michael Kennedy: Without a doubt. Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: I just feel like people so often go, well, it's a computer
Michael Kennedy: and it's wrong, so it's trash. It's no good.
Michael Kennedy: well was it 95% right because that's really helpful this is so important and there are
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: several things in there firstly I think when after our chat champion moment Jeremy Howard noticed a
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: complaint that people like oh I need to chat with like it doesn't do the thing the first time and I
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: need to correct it and Jeremy was like what type of human don't you need to have a conversation with
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: to learn learn stuff um the other thing is in all of these well nearly all of these systems now
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you have memory and cursor for example has cursor rules whereas if you notice stuff that it doesn't
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: that it does or doesn't do put it in the rules you can have project specific rules you can have
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: cursor uh general rules um this type of stuff um such as always explain your reasoning and to
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: your point i don't think these things think but they mimic reasoning and thought um in in in pretty
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: sophisticated ways. So I totally agree with that. Also, use these things to not only write code,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but to write tests for code producers, right? To debug, to add assertions. Now, also,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: make sure you're always reading the code on average that it writes. If things are really
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: important, it's about your appetite for risk. Maybe if things are really important, make sure
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you know what the code does and read it. If things aren't as important, maybe you don't need to. And
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: an example I'll give there is one of the biggest wins here is being able to vibe code your own
Michael Kennedy: data viewers. So let's say I'm building... 100%. I agree with you on this.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Incredible, right? So if I'm building an LLM powered app where... Okay, building an LLM powered
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: out and I've got all these conversations, I can build a vibe code, a custom, a bespoke custom
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: viewer to view that. If it's an agent that writes emails, I can even build a viewer that displays
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: the conversations as emails or whatever it may be, right? Now, I need to make sure that it's
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: displaying the correct information. So I need to make sure that my traces are actually looking
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: looking correct so i need to understand that code but the ins and outs of the front end it's building
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: not not the biggest deal for me so figure out what's important and and what isn't um there's
Michael Kennedy: so many tools like this that are like it's not me worth taking a week to write that but wouldn't it
Michael Kennedy: be cool if i had that and nothing depends on it it's kind of like its own side little utility
Michael Kennedy: there's no it's not a building block that's going to become an important foundational thing it just
Michael Kennedy: If it works, you're like, that's awesome, I have that.
Michael Kennedy: There's people who have got to take advantage of just going like,
Michael Kennedy: oh, I need a utility that does X,
Michael Kennedy: or I need a view in our admin section of the web app that does this.
Michael Kennedy: Nothing depends on it.
Michael Kennedy: If it works, amazing.
Michael Kennedy: If it doesn't, well, it didn't exist anyway, so whatever.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: There's so many opportunities.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I love this so much.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I want to take a slight detour because it's so important.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I actually think the surface area of what software is, is expanding and changing completely.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So let's just look at, take a bit of a sociological big picture look at history where software,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: classically, has been very expensive to build, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You've needed to pay a lot of not inexpensive engineers to build out a sophisticated product
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: for that reason, you've had to get a lot of demand.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You've had to have a lot of service area of the market.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: What that's meant is that you've needed to cover
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: a lot of edge cases to satisfy a large market
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: so that you can make revenue based on the costs
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: that you're accruing, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, with the ability to even vibe code
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: or use AI-assisted coding to build this type of stuff,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: it changes what we can build.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and what it needs, what type of people it needs to satisfy.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So that's why the conversation of like vibe coding
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: is going to bury Salesforce or SaaS
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: versus like old men screaming at clouds,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: vibe coding sucks or whatever it is,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: misses the entire middle ground
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: of the types of things that are possible.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I do think internal products such as,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: we've talked about data viewers,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: internal products such as, you know,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Lots of companies are ripping out their marketing automation stacks and building things internally
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: through to, I mean, I've got a friend who built a chess tutor app, which, I mean, it's
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: not chess.com, but like a hundred of his friends use it, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So the idea of the different types of software we can build now and thinking about, you know,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: ephemeral software or just-in-time software,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: disposable software, fast software
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: that we can build to solve a problem right now
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and then move on.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I think we need to shift our mental model
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: of what software actually is.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Oh, you're on mute, Michael.
Michael Kennedy: Thank you.
Michael Kennedy: I 100% agree.
Michael Kennedy: And it's such an exciting time.
Michael Kennedy: I also think this actually has an implication
Michael Kennedy: for PyPI packages
Michael Kennedy: and a lot of these just external packages.
Michael Kennedy: So think about the ones you use.
Michael Kennedy: This is not going to happen for Pandas or Polars or Jupyter or something like that.
Michael Kennedy: But how often have you gone like, "Oh, I need a package that will let me look up both my IPv4 and IPv6 IP address."
Michael Kennedy: And you'd take that as a dependency.
Michael Kennedy: That's like using one function out of whatever thing you grab that might give you that information.
Michael Kennedy: and there's a lot more opportunity to have fewer building blocks
Michael Kennedy: and dependencies that you need in your application.
Michael Kennedy: If you can just say, hey, agent thing,
Michael Kennedy: I need this and put it in its own file and boom.
Michael Kennedy: And now you're not dependent on,
Michael Kennedy: well, did that thing upgrade to Python 3.15?
Michael Kennedy: Sorry, you're stuck.
Michael Kennedy: It didn't.
Michael Kennedy: You know what I mean?
Michael Kennedy: Like it's, you were sort of free from these like little weird,
Michael Kennedy: I depend on this whole tree of dependencies
Michael Kennedy: because I need one little piece of functionality.
Michael Kennedy: You can vendor end stuff a lot easier if it's low stakes.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Absolutely.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The other thing that I think AI assisted coding
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I've seen help with is,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: now this will be a bit controversial,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but it's going from prototype to production.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And what I really mean by that,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: let's say your production stack is in like Databricks,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Spark, whatever.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You can prototype, write your pandas code.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And then because once again,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Spark, Databricks, all that documentation is in training data,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you can then convert it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: relatively easily. But of course, read, test your code that you're pushing to prod just as you would
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: with a junior software engineer, right? Yeah. The other thing is some gotchas with this.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It'll do lots of things you don't ask it to do, okay? Such as...
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It will just start downloading packages, for example, if you're trying to write some code,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: right? And it will, so it'll do lots of things you don't ask it to do. And it will also do things
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you ask it to not do, right? So you'll say only write in one file and Devon, for example, like
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: will create like nested sub directories, each with 15 notebooks, right? Or something,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: something like that. It will also forget lots of things in your, in your conversation, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So make sure to remind it of things.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It will do something called dead looping.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And this is one of the most frustrating and pernicious things,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: depending on how long the loop is.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But it will try to solve your most recent concern.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It will really optimize locally around the conversation.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And so it will solve that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Then another error will appear, and it will solve that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it will, another error appear, it will solve that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And after a while, it might actually go back to the initial state.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So that's what deadlocking is.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah, yeah.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it just cycles, yeah.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Three, five, seven, nine.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So be very careful about that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Solutions are get it to zoom out.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Say, hey, let's zoom out
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and have a holistic conversation about this.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, this is wild.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: This is how we're interacting with software as well.
Michael Kennedy: It's part of the-
Michael Kennedy: It's science fiction.
Michael Kennedy: It really is.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But write product requirement drops with it before any code.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, it may still just start writing code,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: even when you tell it to do that, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Plan with it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Have empathy for your super excited, bright, fast, forgetful intern, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Also, you know, I've really embraced this plan thing.
Michael Kennedy: All my major projects have a plans folder.
Michael Kennedy: And every time I start, I create a markdown file.
Michael Kennedy: I say, we're going to plan it out.
Michael Kennedy: I want you to write in this markdown file what we're going to do.
Michael Kennedy: And I'll do that with a really expensive model, you know,
Michael Kennedy: like a thinking something or whatever.
Michael Kennedy: And it'll do it.
Michael Kennedy: Then I'll switch.
Michael Kennedy: I'll completely throw away that chat.
Michael Kennedy: get another one, a little lower model,
Michael Kennedy: say, we're going to do phase one of this plan.
Michael Kennedy: Let's go.
Michael Kennedy: And then two, and then three.
Michael Kennedy: And every time I say, when you're done,
Michael Kennedy: you update the plan so you know where we are
Michael Kennedy: and what we've done, what's not.
Michael Kennedy: And it's tremendously successful.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Absolutely.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And also, there is a concern of
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: sometimes you want memory from one chat.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Like sometimes a chat just degrades.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So start a new conversation.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And there are clever ways,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: different for different products and models,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but to get it to summarize the conversation so far,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Like literally say, I'm going to take another instance of you.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Let's squash this so I can pass the important memories to it and so on.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The other thing is Cursor, a lot of these products have,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: it used to be called YOLO mode on Cursor.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Like Y-O-L-O mode, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Where it just executes.
Michael Kennedy: I run in YOLO mode, by the way.
Michael Kennedy: I do it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Man, I have too much anxiety around that.
Michael Kennedy: So here's the thing that's really gotten that I've really noticed that's interesting is my Git discipline is significantly better now that I'm – if I do that.
Michael Kennedy: So I'll open it up and I'll go and I'll start having a chat and I'll make sure everything is checked in.
Michael Kennedy: I might do a separate branch if I think it's going to go bonkers.
Michael Kennedy: And then it'll do a little bit of work.
Michael Kennedy: And I'm like, okay, that's successful.
Michael Kennedy: So I'll stage those changes but not even commit them.
Michael Kennedy: and then I'll let it keep going and it'll create more work
Michael Kennedy: and I see if it's successful, I'll just put it
Michael Kennedy: and then eventually I'll commit it at the end.
Michael Kennedy: It won't even push it necessarily.
Michael Kennedy: And then you can also, while it's running,
Michael Kennedy: have the get diff window open
Michael Kennedy: and you can just sort of see what it's doing
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: by looking at the diffs that start to appear.
Michael Kennedy: And so that's why I'm okay with YOLO mode
Michael Kennedy: because I can always just get revert and we're fine again.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Totally.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And also, I didn't mention this,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but these AI assistants are great at looking at diffs with you.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I also, I'm really thinking through what happens
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: when we have so much AI generated code.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I think part of the future of work,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I don't want to get too sci-fi-esque,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but how many agents can you manage simultaneously?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Like maybe the SuperSpa employees
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: will be people who can manage a hundred agents.
Michael Kennedy: It's like the revenge of the program manager.
Michael Kennedy: I'm telling you.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's so true.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And in fact, project management, product management are some of the most important skills moving forward.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But also, when you have so many agents generating code, what happens to CICD?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: What happens to Jenkins?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: There's going to be a whole new space of products and agents that may deal with these types of systems, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Look during the Industrial Revolution, what sprung up when looms appeared and the satellite industries that happened there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So I think we're talking about job automation and job displacement,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but the amount of new jobs that will become available,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I'm actually very excited about.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And we'll put in the show notes, please,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but there's an essay by Tim O'Reilly,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and I did a podcast with him about it, actually,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: that we can link to if you're up for it,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: called The End of Programming As We Know It.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Okay.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And he essentially, with his great depth of historical knowledge
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and his forward thinking through vectors
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: prevents a really wonderful vision
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and ideas around where software is heading.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Exactly.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, very cool.
Michael Kennedy: What about exploring data?
Michael Kennedy: So we've been talking about mostly writing data,
Michael Kennedy: testing, writing code, testing code
Michael Kennedy: in the context of data science.
Michael Kennedy: But I think it's actually really pretty powerful to say,
Michael Kennedy: here's a CSV.
Michael Kennedy: This is basically what it means.
Michael Kennedy: Let's start looking at, get me some graphs,
Michael Kennedy: pull me out some trends.
Michael Kennedy: What's important?
Michael Kennedy: What do you see that I didn't see?
Michael Kennedy: What do you think about this exploratory analysis side of it?
Michael Kennedy: And that doesn't even worry you about,
Michael Kennedy: is there maybe a bug in the code
Michael Kennedy: because I don't want to put it in production, right?
Michael Kennedy: It's just fooling around to get a jumpstart on understanding.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: - So firstly, exploratory data analysis is one
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: of a scientist and data scientist's most important jobs, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So the question then becomes is how can we get AI to, you know,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: help us, you know, see what's happening that's so integral to what we do.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And the truth is they're wonderful.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: They can be wonderful at pulling out insights that I just haven't noticed
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: or I don't even think about how to visualize.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, if I ask it to find the mean or median, it may suck at that on average
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: unless it writes the code to do so, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But when you get it to do EDA or exploratory data analysis,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: it will provide insights that I haven't thought of.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So one example I saw recently from a client
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: was throwing in like thousands of rows of customer data
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and website data of customers.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it immediately showed clusters of high usage versus low usage.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You could see power users. You could see power users who spent a lot on the platform.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You could see power users who didn't spend much on the platform.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And this is the type of work that takes hours for data scientists to sift through and develop hypotheses around.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So when we're talking about, you know, data science is exploration and hypothesis driven, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So when we're talking about exploration and hypothesis driven data science, it's wonderful there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And once again, this isn't to replace what we do, but it's to help us.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's having a thought partner.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Which is fast.
Michael Kennedy: Like beyond the computer, a different bicycle of the mind of a sort.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, maybe like a little, maybe it's like an e-bike of the mind.
Michael Kennedy: What do you think?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I love it.
Michael Kennedy: I love e-bikes.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: They're awesome.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I especially, because I live in Sydney, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So getting to the beach, it's actually quite hilly.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: depending where where you are um and the other thing i
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: yeah when so hopefully we have time to talk about this but something i do a lot of work on
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: is what i call uh evaluation driven development um first lm and ai powered applications um where
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: A really important part of this is error analysis and failure analysis.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So seeing where your applications fail.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So let's say we're building a chatbot, which is RAG.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So it has some corpus of documents and it retrieves stuff from it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And we want to interact with it, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: When we're building that, some of the first steps and ongoing process is seeing what failure modes they are.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Is it hallucinating or is it not retrieving things correctly?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Is it looking at the wrong documents?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: These types of things.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And you do that to drive the development and iterative process of AI-powered software.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, you can also use AI to look at that and look at the results in the data exploration.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it can really bring out a lot of different failure modes.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It can say, hey, look at this cluster of conversations where the user finally got the correct response, but they asked to be connected to a representative first, and they didn't get connected to a representative.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So this is actually an example where the conversation looks like it's resolved.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: the support ticket was resolved or whatever it is.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But there's a deep failure mode within there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So AI can be very good in terms of the data exploration
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and hypothesis driving process with that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So that was an example.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But yeah, should we get into building LLM-powered software?
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, sure.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So I wonder whether you'd like to bring up the figure
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: that I will talk through because I know there'll be people listening. And I'll share it in the chat
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: with you. Ah, great. So this is a slightly tongue in cheek figure, but it speaks to real pain we
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: have. So on the x-axis, we have time. And we're talking about building software. On the y-axis,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: we have excitement or dopamine, if you will, if you want to measure it. And for the scientists
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: out there, I apologize for not having units on my axes, but it's all good. We know with traditional
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: software, excitement increases over time. Things are pretty boring at the start. You have a hello
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: world and basic features and add unit tests. Then you scale and optimize and load balance. And
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: over time, excitement increases and increases and increases. This is absolutely inverted with
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: generative AI powered software, right? Where you have a flashy demo at the start. You're like,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: wow check this out okay then you're like oh wait does it actually work all that like can someone
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: else use it and so you have issues with basic functionality then so excitement goes down
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: um then you're like oh no all these hallucinations excitement goes down then you have monitoring
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: challenges you're like how can i even look at all my conversations and tool calls and actions and
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: this type of stuff um excitement goes down then you have integration issues how do i integrate into my
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: enterprise stack uh excitement goes down again and i i don't think it's a coincidence um that you
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: know this is one of the most exciting technologies of a generation that's um totally addicted to
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: instagram as well right um but the question is and a lot of work i i do is in helping people
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: raise the curve not change anything not even change the excitement of the flashy demo but just
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Make sure that excitement goes up and up and up as you build.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And once again, there's no free lunch.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You've got to do this the hard way, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And so this is something, and a short plug for a course I teach,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but this is something I teach a lot on,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and I teach a Maven course building LM powered applications
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: for data science and software engineers
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: with my colleague, Stefan Krauchik,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: who he works on agent infrastructure at Salesforce.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I bring a lot of the data and ML stuff.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: He brings a lot of the ops stuff.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But yeah, in this course, we teach a lot of these things.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And the way we do that, one way to think about it
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: is what we call evaluation-driven development.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So that's not necessarily having like very sophisticated evals
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and tests and that type of stuff to start,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But it's about having a sense of where you want your product to go and having a sense of evaluation of how to drive it in that direction.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And the skill set that's required for this is so similar to people who've built data science and ML-powered products, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So it's a curiosity to explore data.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's a hacker mindset.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's experimenting with different tools.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And what have we been doing in the PyDataStack?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I mean, look at the data viz landscape in Python.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I think it was maybe PyCon 2018 that Jake Vanderplus,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I think, first time gave his talk, you know,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: data visualization in Python.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And, you know, there were so many tools one could use there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's this type of mindset you need.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And then in terms of the product workflow,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: how you make sure you don't kind of go down this curve,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: lose excitement in what I call proof of concept purgatory.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: People call the plateau of productivity.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: There are all types of fun names about it.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But what you do is you use the machine learning mindset,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: which is get some data in and out of your system.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: If you don't have users yet,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you can generate synthetic data to do so, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Then you label it, pass or fail initially.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And this is in the spirit of iteration.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You give it a failure mode,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: such as it was hallucination, retrieval error,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: wrong tool call.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And a tool call essentially is what an agent does.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So an agent is an LLM plus tool calls.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: A tool call could be ping an API, send an email, whatever it is.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Agent plus tool call in some while loop or for loop, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And so you have, did this particular interaction pass or fail?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: What was the failure mode?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And then how do I fix these particular failure modes?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I mean, one way to do this initially,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: depending on the complexity of your system,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: is to put all of this in a spreadsheet
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and do a pivot table.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I know AI engineers hate it
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: when I tell them to do pivot tables,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: but if you rank order,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: use a pivot table to rank order your failure modes
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: by frequency,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: then you can see what to fix first.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And if it's a retrieval error,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: maybe you want to fix the rag part of your system
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and the retrieval part, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: As opposed to the generative part.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So focus on your embeddings or chunks.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: If it's a tool call,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: focus on how that tool call is defined.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and heuristics that the LLM uses there.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: A lot of the time--
Michael Kennedy: - I would like to add, well, this is great.
Michael Kennedy: I would like to add that you can use
Michael Kennedy: those agentic coding tools to help build better analytics
Michael Kennedy: or other support.
Michael Kennedy: So if you're like, God, we don't really have,
Michael Kennedy: we can't really track that, right?
Michael Kennedy: Like, well, give it half an hour and you can,
Michael Kennedy: you know what I mean?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: - Exactly.
Michael Kennedy: - And so you got to kind of think out of the box
Michael Kennedy: and be a little creative there.
Michael Kennedy: Maybe build an MCP server that specializes in solving,
Michael Kennedy: you know, a specialized LLM that addresses a shortcoming
Michael Kennedy: that you can then force it to use the MCP server
Michael Kennedy: and work more constrained or whatever.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Exactly, exactly.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And as we kind of hinted at earlier,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: one of the wacky things here is that a lot of this comes down to prompting
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and people like, should I fine tune or prompt engineer or rag
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: or that type of stuff?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Prompt and prompt and prompt initially,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: because you can get so much lift by prompting.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Now, if it is actually a retrieval error,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: perhaps you want to improve your embeddings
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: or your chunking strategy or that type of stuff.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The other thing is, of course, data, metadata, data ingestion.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Draw an architectural diagram of your system
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: where you see, you know, you have your RAG,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you have your output, you have your embeddings,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you have your OCR, or if you've got PDS,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: however you're ingesting your data,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: a huge amount of the time,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: fixing how you do your OCR on your PDFs will be far more significant lift than switching out to
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Claude Sonnet 4.5. Okay. And on that point, I totally understand why people want to try
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: the newest and sexiest model. And I'm not telling people not to. What I'm saying is focus on the
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: fundamentals. And then when you have, you know, this set of evals of like, of labeled data of what,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: what works, what doesn't.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You want a test set, essentially, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Like in machine learning.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So it's the same process.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You have this test set, your gold standard,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: which ideally covers,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: has coverage over all your failure modes.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You want eval coverage.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Then when you switch out to a new model,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: you can see how it performed on your test set.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Imagine that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Imagine being able to switch out a model
Michael Kennedy: and seeing what's up there, right?
Michael Kennedy: Be able to say it's better concretely with data,
Michael Kennedy: not just it feels better.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah, exactly.
Michael Kennedy: All right.
Michael Kennedy: We're pretty much, you go ahead.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I was just going to add one more thing.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: There are all these eval conversations about we don't want these evals.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: We want online evals.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And then there are people do things only by vibes.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And all of these things are absolutely valid as well.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I think it's a healthy combination for whatever your product needs at any point in time.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: We're pretty much out of time.
Michael Kennedy: But I do want to take just a couple minutes, literally, and get your thoughts on people coming into the industry.
Michael Kennedy: Data scientists who are just graduating now
Michael Kennedy: or they got their first job
Michael Kennedy: or they're about to get their first job.
Michael Kennedy: I imagine this is something of a scary time to think,
Michael Kennedy: well, now I'm not just competing with all the other people.
Michael Kennedy: Now these AI things are fighting against me getting a job as well.
Michael Kennedy: But I think it's both a blessing and a curse.
Michael Kennedy: But what do you think?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Yeah, I totally agree.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Focus on three things.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: What value you can deliver?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: What's your skill as a data scientist?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it is looking at data.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It is building.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And it is tying that to business value.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So if you focus on your skills and you build, build, build,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and consistently tie it to business value,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I think you'll go a long way.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And this actually speaks to how we think about evaluation
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: more generally.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I do want to give a shout out to a Sydney-based company
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: called Lorikeet that they build customer support agents
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: for all types of industries.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And when they do evaluation, they always evaluate,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: was the ticket solved or not?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: That's the most important evaluation.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: It's not, did this LLM call result in what we wanted it to be
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: or anything along those lines.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Of course, once they see a failure, they tie it back.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: to these more technical LLM-based failure modes.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But I wonder if, yeah,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: maybe Google Lorikeet AI or something like that.
Michael Kennedy: I had it in another tab.
Michael Kennedy: I don't know.
Michael Kennedy: I'll get it back.
Michael Kennedy: Oh, good.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Hold on.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And one thing I love about,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and I'm indexing on them,
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: There are lots of companies that do this.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: But one thing that's very interesting about them is that their pricing model is ticket resolution based, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So if they've built a concierge or customer service agent for you, you pay based on how many tickets are resolved.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: A lot of their competitors, their pricing is based on tokens, right?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: Because that's what they pay for.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And in terms of aligning incentives, having it based around resolution is incredibly important for how you build as well.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And the reason, the question was, what should early stage data scientists focus on?
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: The reason I detoured on that story is supreme focus on business value, how your skills can be tied to business value via building stuff.
Michael Kennedy: Yeah.
Michael Kennedy: Awesome.
Michael Kennedy: It's great advice.
Michael Kennedy: And I will just throw one more thing out there for people is don't let these AI tools undercut your desire to actually learn the details.
Michael Kennedy: If you just go like, all right, I asked it,
Michael Kennedy: and it gave me the answer, and it just streamed by,
Michael Kennedy: and you didn't pay attention, you're doing it wrong.
Michael Kennedy: You've got to stop, read, pay attention, question,
Michael Kennedy: why did it do that?
Michael Kennedy: You can even ask it, why did you do this?
Michael Kennedy: Rather than that way, it might give you a documentation link.
Michael Kennedy: You've got to stay active, and it's so easy to just go next,
Michael Kennedy: next, next, because it's exciting that it's building something.
Michael Kennedy: Absolutely.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: And I will add one other thing there, which is we need to carve out
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: these things won't always work.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: You can spend a day working with AI
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and make less progress than if you'd done it yourself as well.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I want to be very clear about that.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: What we all need to do is figure out organizations
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: we can work at, work with, and then time ourselves
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: to experiment with these seriously emerging
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and rapidly changing technologies.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So it won't always be wins is my point.
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: So don't get discouraged when it isn't.
Michael Kennedy: awesome Hugo thank you for being on the show sharing what you've been up to your yeah absolutely
Michael Kennedy: I'll put a link to your podcasts your courses stuff like that in the show notes for people
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: I'd love that oh and I mentioned this to you earlier but um always love talk python of course
Hugo Bowne-Anderson: and I'm so grateful for having me on three times and I'd love to offer your audience 20% off my
Michael Kennedy: course as well so we'll include that that link in the show notes beautiful we'll put it put it right
Michael Kennedy: about the link. All right. Well, thanks for being here. We live in weird and amazing and crazy times.
Michael Kennedy: And yeah, I'm not leaving with that. On the journey together. Thanks. That's right. See you later.
Michael Kennedy: Bye, everyone. Ciao.
Michael Kennedy: out.